<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Astrologaster, or, The figure-caster Rather the arraignment of artlesse astrologers, and fortune-tellers, that cheat many ignorant people vnder the pretence of foretelling things to come, of telling things that are past, finding out things that are lost, expounding dreames, calculating deaths and natiuities, once againe brought to the barre. By Iohn Melton.</title>
            <author>Melton, John, Sir, d. 1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 190 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07418</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17804</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112560</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847808</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847808</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12869</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07418)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12869)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 966:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Astrologaster, or, The figure-caster Rather the arraignment of artlesse astrologers, and fortune-tellers, that cheat many ignorant people vnder the pretence of foretelling things to come, of telling things that are past, finding out things that are lost, expounding dreames, calculating deaths and natiuities, once againe brought to the barre. By Iohn Melton.</title>
                  <author>Melton, John, Sir, d. 1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 80 p., folded table   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Barnard Alsop, for Edward Blackmore, and are to be sold in Paules Churchyard, at the signe of the Blazing-Starre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The figure-caster.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12869:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12869:1"/>
            <p>ASTROLOGASTER, <hi>OR,</hi> THE FIGVRE-CASTER. Rather the Arraignment of Artleſſe Aſtrologers, and Fortune-tellers, that cheat many ignorant people vnder the pretence of foretelling things to <hi>come, of telling things that are paſt, finding out things that are loſt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding</hi> Dreames, calculating Deaths and Natiuities, <hi>once againe brought to the Barre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Iohn Melton.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Stultorum plena ſunt omnia.</p>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Barnard Alſop,</hi> for <hi>Edward Blackmore,</hi> and are to be ſold in <hi>Paules</hi> Churchyard, at the Signe of the <hi>Blazing-Starre.</hi> 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12869:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12869:2"/>
            <head>TO THE DEARE GIVER and preſeruer of my Life and Being, my very lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Father, Maſter <hi>Euan Melton,</hi> your moſt Dutifull <hi>Sonne,</hi> Iohn Melton, <hi>faithfully and freely offers</hi> on the altar of my pureſt affection, <hi>this Sacrifice of my Duty and</hi> Obedience.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Miſterious <hi>Egyptians</hi> when they could not elegantly with their Penſels deſcribe the true condition, or Nature, either of Timerous, Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, mild or fearefull man, would excellently with their Penſils in liuely cullors, limbe forth on a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the ful ſhape &amp; portraiture of a Hart, a Lyon, Lamb, or Hare. So I though not ſo Hyerogliphicall as they, ſeeing I cannot ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe my duty to you with my Tongue, ſtriue to paint it forth in this Booke, which is one Embleme both of my Loue, and Labor, of my loue in preſenting it to you, of my labor in pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning it for you. For God ſels nothing to Man without the price of lobour, And howſoeuer the purblinde Ignorant, that only ſee with their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral &amp; not Intellectualleies may ſurmiſe, yet Art is the fellow of ſweat and labour and the Muſes haue no other Temples to dwell in but ſtudious and laborious boſomes. Sloth and Riches neuer begat Art, but pouerty and Induſtry. Mony buyes Houſes and Lands, but Study the Sciences: And deare Sir, to you that alwaies loued Art I hope nothing can come more pleaſing then a Booke (which is the child of Art) for Bookes that <hi>Menerua</hi>-like, are alwayes borne without a Mother are the forward Infants that ſpeake for their fathers as ſoone as they are born: They are dumb Orators, who though they want both Tongue and Sence yet are the faithfulleſt ſpeakers. They are the witneſſes of Time the
<pb facs="tcp:12869:3"/>lights of Truth, the life of Memory, that make preſent times ſpeake with the paſt, and both paſt and preſent of our owne. The World it ſelfe is a Book conſiſting of foure leaues: Fire, Aire, Earth and Water; whoſe letters are Stars, Birds, Beaſts and Fiſhes: And (Man that is the Epitome and Abſtract of the World) is a Book conſiſting of two leaues; Soule and Body: whoſe Letters are his good and bad Affections. But I will ſay no more in the commendation of Books, becauſe they can ſtrongly defend and truly commend themſelues: as for my Booke, rather your Booke, although it haue not that Life, Soule, Spirit, Quinteſſence, &amp; Elixar of wit that quickens others, yet the old ſaying helps me.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nullum eſſe librum tam malum vnde aliquid</l>
               <l>Boni diſcerpere non poſſis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Receiue it then deare ſir, not as mine, but your owne, and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer you may eſteeme of it, yet I will remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your dutifull and euer louing Sonne,</hi> Iohn Melton.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Chamber</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iune the 10. 1620.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="symbol">
            <pb facs="tcp:12869:3"/>
            <head>A Symbole made on the Name of his very louing <hi>Father, Maſter</hi> Euan Melton.</head>
            <p>E<hi rend="sup">1</hi>V<hi rend="sup">2</hi>A<hi rend="sup">3</hi>N<hi rend="sup">4</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>E<hi rend="sup">1</hi>Ver V<hi rend="sup">2</hi>Allew A<hi rend="sup">3</hi>Rt N<hi rend="sup">4</hi>Obly</hi>
            </p>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">5</hi>E<hi rend="sup">6</hi>L<hi rend="sup">7</hi>T<hi rend="sup">8</hi>O<hi rend="sup">9</hi>N<hi rend="sup">10</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>M<hi rend="sup">5</hi>Vch E<hi rend="sup">6</hi>Xperience L<hi rend="sup">7</hi>Earning T<hi rend="sup">8</hi> Eacheth O<hi rend="sup">9</hi>Bdurate N<hi rend="sup">10</hi>Atures.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:12869:4"/>
            <head>To his witty and ingenious friend Maſter <hi>Iohn Melton:</hi>
            </head>
            <l>I cannot chuſe but laugh to thinke how all</l>
            <l>The broode of Figure-caſting-knaues will braule</l>
            <l>When they by chance or rather miſchance looke</l>
            <l>Vpon the title of thy well writ booke:</l>
            <l>Which in a True-borne-ſtraine of wit diſplayes.</l>
            <l>Their groſe abuſes and how many wayes,</l>
            <l>They cheat old women, men, and maids, and ſuch</l>
            <l>That build vpon their Art and do not gruch</l>
            <l>To giue them mony to be cheated when,</l>
            <l>They loſe things that no Art can finde agen.</l>
            <l>But now I hope they will be wiſer ſince</l>
            <l>Thy Pen hath truly blazd their Impudence,</l>
            <l>And when they loſe gold, rather then beſtow</l>
            <l>More on a Knaue; to let the firſt gold goe.</l>
            <l>For it is meere improuidence to care,</l>
            <l>For things drownd in the Ocean of deſpaire.</l>
            <l>Therefore if all beleeuing fooles could finde</l>
            <l>Like thee, their pollitike tricks wherewith they blinde,</l>
            <l>Their eaſie Natures; they, would then proclame,</l>
            <l>All Figure-ſellers, Knaues and ſharpely blame</l>
            <l>Themſelues for being guld, and neuer more</l>
            <l>Whatere they loſe, frequent them as before.</l>
            <l>Then would all Artleſſe Empericks forſake.</l>
            <l>Cheating and ſtudy lying Almanacks.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohn Maſlin, <hi>Maſter of Art and ſometime Student of</hi> Trinity <hi>Colledge in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:12869:4"/>
            <head>To his moſt deare and trueſt of friends Maſter <hi>Iohn Melton,</hi> and in the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation <hi>of his witty Poem.</hi> Aſtrologaſter.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>PHoebus</hi> prouide a Garland for thine Heire,</l>
            <l>That hath deſeru'd ſo well, and make him weare</l>
            <l>It on his temples; let th'immortall wreaths</l>
            <l>Of Lawrell crowne, him while his rich Muſe breaths</l>
            <l>Which will be euer. A good Poets name,</l>
            <l>Liues after he is dead: Non ſpotted fame:</l>
            <l>Cannot be mortall: why? becauſe whats good,</l>
            <l>Can neuer periſh, it may be with ſtood</l>
            <l>A while by Enuy, but ſhe will aduance</l>
            <l>At laſt her ſelfe aboue dull Ignorance,</l>
            <l>And that foule ſnake-eyed-Hagge that ſtill doth ſtriue</l>
            <l>To wound her that by wounding doth ſuruiue.</l>
            <l>Then my Ingenious noble friend reioyce</l>
            <l>And though thou heareſt ſome Figure-Caſters voyce,</l>
            <l>Like a Portentous Rauens croake and cry,</l>
            <l>Thy Books not only ill writ, but doth lye,</l>
            <l>Be not diſturbd, for know theirs none finds fault</l>
            <l>With thoſe that ſcourge vice, but thoſe men are naught.</l>
            <l>None hates the righteous Iudge, but thoſe that ſtand</l>
            <l>At'h Barre before him holding vp their hand.</l>
            <l>The vertuous loue him knowing that the Law</l>
            <l>He executes keeps hell-borne-vice in awe</l>
            <l>Then let all Knaues let all Impoſtors ſwell</l>
            <l>All honeſt men will ſay thou haſt done well</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohn Hancocke, <hi>Batchelor of Art, and Student of</hi> Brazen-noſe <hi>Colledge in Oxford.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:12869:5"/>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>The intent of the Author in this worke is firſt to confute all Figure-Caſters, by the</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Diuine Law,</item>
                     <item>Imperiall Law,</item>
                     <item>Cannon Law: <hi>by</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Phyloſophy,</item>
                     <item>Common ſence <hi>&amp;</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Reaſon.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secondly, to ouerthrow the abſurd opinions of many</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Phyloſophers</item>
                     <item>Aſtronomers.</item>
                     <item>Geographers.</item>
                     <item>Coſmographers.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thirdly, to vnfold the darke and abſtruſe Anſwers of the</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Delphian, <hi>rather Deuilliſh</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Oracles.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fourthly, and laſtly, to ſhew the Sympathy and Correſpondency that is betweene the Roguiſh Coniurers, and Romiſh Impoſtors, in their</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Ceremonies,</item>
                     <item>Superſtitious</item>
                     <item>Deceits, <hi>and</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Couſenages.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Horat. Epiſt. Lib. 1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <l>— Si quid nouiſti rectius iſtis</l>
               <l>Candidus imperti; ſi non vis vtere mecum.</l>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12869:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ASTROLOGASTER,</hi> OR, THE FIGVRE-CASTER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was about the Heart of Summer, (when the Celeſtiall Dogge belch't from his burning Galls infectious Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes to poyſon frayle Mortalitie) that I walk't into a friends Garden of mine, not farre diſtant from this ſumptuous (but ſinfull) Citie, to ſent the freſh and coole Aire, that did breathe on thoſe ſweet-ſmelling flowers. But I no ſooner entred into this <hi>Microcoſme</hi> of Sweetneſſe, but the Amenitie, Neatneſſe, Elegance, and Splendor of the Place did ſo tickle and delight my ſences, that I thought it rather a Celeſtiall Paradice, then a Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtriall Garden. The glorious Fires that in the peace of Midnight gild the rich Roofe of Heauen, ſhew'd but dimme to thoſe bright flowers that in the day time did il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminate that place; ſo that a hundred times I did wiſh I had <hi>Argus</hi> hundred eyes, that I might alwayes ſee them, or <hi>Catullus</hi> ſweet ſenting noſe, that I might alwayes ſmell them. The <hi>Arabtan</hi> Odours and <hi>Indian</hi> Drugs were but
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12869:6"/>Weeds, compared to the flowers that did bleſſe thoſe banks. The Gardens of <hi>Adonis, Alcinous, Tantalus, Heſperides,</hi> or the Bankes of <hi>Po</hi> were but the Types of this Reall and Eſſentiall ſweetneſſe; for all things grew ſo beautifull and pleaſant, as if Nature had concluded, that whatſoeuer hath beene eximious or braue in former Ages, ſhould then dwell there, for it was <hi>Floras</hi> Pallace, her Standing-Houſe, and her Spicerie, from whence ſhe did breathe forth her ſweetneſſe to euery Climate.</p>
            <p>When I beheld the induſtrious Gardiner grafting young Syens, me thought (with my Minds eyes) I beheld <hi>Diocle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> the Prince exerciſing himſelfe in the delightſome la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of Agriculture; and that which all <hi>Africa</hi> admired, <hi>Maſſiniſſa</hi> walking among his Quick-ſets: I could not be perſwaded, but I ſaw the valiant <hi>Romans,</hi> learned <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> wiſe <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> and wrangling <hi>Lawyers;</hi> their Armes, Oratorie, Moralitie, the lowd and troubleſome Barre layd aſide, quietly and peaceably repoſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues on thoſe Bankes: <hi>Tarquinius</hi> the King cutting off the heads of Poppyes, as if they had beene the heads of ſo many rebellious ſubiects; <hi>Cato</hi> the Cenſor writing in the prayſe of Husbandry; <hi>Scilla,</hi> after his Dictatorſhip, and <hi>Luculius,</hi> after his <hi>Aſiatick</hi> Warre.</p>
            <p>But as I was ſeriouſly looking ouer this <hi>Aeden</hi> of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, my eyes tooke notice of a withered banke of flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, hanging downe their weather-beaten heads, that not ſeuen dayes before had flouriſhed in their full prime; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating vnto Man, that the beautie of all Mundane and Earthly pleaſures haue no perpetuitie. Not farre from them grew a ſweet companie of freſh and redolent flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that like ſo many young Gallants, thought the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their glory would neuer vaniſh, but that their beautie and colour was dyed in ſuch a deepe graine of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuitie, that neyther the violence of a Storme, the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning North-Winde, nor the heat of the Mid-day Sunne, could beat downe, nippe, or wither them. And theſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12869:6"/>and flouriſhing Plants were not onely the Emblemes of Mans Mortalitie,<note place="margin">F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ower<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s of Mans 5 Death and Reſurrection.</note> but the true Type of his Death and Reſurrection; of his Death, in their decay; of his Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, in their growth and flouriſhing.</p>
            <p>Euery Tree I ſaw there clad in Natures Liuerie (which is greene) put me in mind of that <hi>Protoplast, Adam</hi> our Great Grandfather, and his Fall: for if hee neuer had tranſgreſt, hee neuer had worne a Sute of greene leaues; and hee neuer had beene cloathed in the Trappings of Sinne, if he ſtill had kept himſelfe Naked, that is, Pure, Sincere, and Spotleſſe. Therefore,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> euery Gallant or prowd Man, that weares Clothes as freſh as the Fields, that bought them, may thinke with themſelues, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they bee neuer ſo rich, yet they weare but the Ragges of their Fore-fathers, Sinne and Tranſgreſſion. The Oake ſtood there like a great Man,<note place="margin">Oake.</note> whoſe curied Brow was incident to the higheſt Inflamations of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, as Thunder, Lightning, Tempeſt, and Raine, while the poore humble Shrub, that grew vnder him,<note place="margin">Shrub</note> like a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented Cottager, laught at the lowdeſt ſtorme that could euer chide. The Pine-tree ſtood like an vpright Man,<note place="margin">Pine-tree.</note> whoſe Conſcience was faire-ſhap't, ſmooth, and euen. The little Gooſe-berry Buſh, laden with fruit,<note place="margin">Gooſe-berry Buſh.</note> did include with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it a Triple Embleme: Firſt, that the greateſt Men haue not alwayes the greateſt Wits, but that a ſmall Body hath often as fertile a Braine: Secondly, that although it had but a few Leaues, yet it had an abundance of Fruit; tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Man, that his Actions ſhould be more then his Words: And laſt of all, that the heauier hee was laden with Fruit, the lower his head bowed to the Earth; tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching rich and learned Men, that the richer and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neder they grow, the more liberall and humble they ſhould bee. The Bramble, as I walk'd by,<note place="margin">Bramble.</note> ſcratch't me by the Legges, which put mee in minde of a griping Lawyer, that neuer meetes with a Clyent, but hee will bee ſure to fleece him, if hee doe not flea him.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12869:7"/>The Lawrell reſembled a conſtant and braue Martyr,<note place="margin">Lawrell.</note> whoſe leaues being torne from him, and flung into the fire, will ſpit and crackle, as if it derided the deuouring flame.<note place="margin">Roſe.</note> The Damaske Roſe lookt like a chaſt and modeſt Virgin, that will bluſh as ſoone as you caſt your eye vpon her;<note place="margin">Primeroſe.</note> and the ſiluer-coloured Primeroſe, that grew neere her, like a ſpotleſſe Conſcience. Mee thought the Muſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rombe was like one of our Melting-Gallants,<note place="margin">Muſhrombe.</note> who held vp his head but for a ſmall time, but periſhed as ſoone as it began to flouriſh.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and many more beſide theſe, I ſaw in that place, growing peaceably by each other: For the Shrub enuyed not the ſublime height of the Oake, nor the Oake the quiet peace the Shrub enioyed. The Daiſie murmured not, that the Roſe ſhould looke ſo beautifull, and ſmell ſo ſweete; nor any Weed complayned, that the Daiſie ſhould haue ſuch a gay Coat: but all, like ſo many honeſt and quiet Houſe-holders dwelling nigh each other, did reioyce at each others happineſſe. But Man, that is made <hi>ad imaginem Dei,</hi> that is the Golden Key, opening the rich Cabinet of all Arts and Sciences, the <hi>Compendium</hi> and <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitome</hi> of the World, cannot liue quietly together, but like ſo many Salamanders, muſt either be burning in the fires of Contention; or like Wolues, liuing on the ſpoyle of Innocence; or like Camelions, turning themſelues into any colour of Miſchiefe, Villany, or Diſſimulation.</p>
            <p>But, as I was wondering at this Place worthy of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, this extaſie of my admiration was broken off by the occaſion of a noyſe I heard not farre from me, which at the firſt was but like the ſoft breathing of a winde, ſighing from the pregnant entrayles of the earth, but by degrees it began to reſemble a Tempeſt, ſayling aloft in the Ayre. When it drew nigher me, I perceiued this Lowdneſſe to be engendred by the euer-mouing tongues of ſome twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Women, that came talking and walking downe an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley (neighbouring very nigh me) and all of them talking
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12869:7"/>together: ſo that although I had an itching deſire to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, and an attentiue eare to heare the ſubiect of their diſcourſe, yet it was as poſſible for me to know what they did talke, as to make them leaue talking. In the Rere of theſe I perceiued an auncient Man (on whoſe head the hand of Age had ſnowed white hayres) come with a graue pace after them; whom I entreated, if it lay within the reach of his knowledge, to reſolue me what the cauſe was ſo many people, and moſt of them Women, ſhould flocke together, or what buſines they ſhould haue in ſuch a remote and by-place as that was, ſo early in the Morning? This old Father without any peeuiſhneſſe (which is a Paſſion inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to Age) firſt ſmil'd in my face, then tooke me by the hand, and began to open the myſterie of their meeting, and his owne being there, in this manner.</p>
            <p>Sonne, ſaid he (for ſo I may properly call thee, becauſe Smoothneſſe and Alacritie, the Characters of Youth, ſit on thy vn wrinkled for head) theſe Women your eyes did lately take notice of, are Creatures ſo ignorantly obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, that neyther the mild entreatie of a Friend can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them from their follyes, nor the bad report of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie diſſwade them from their peruerſeneſſe. The Party to whom they come, is a Bird, of whoſe kinde I thinke there are but few liuing, for he profeſſeth himſelfe to be a Wiſe-man; and the cauſe of their comming, is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued either of Money, Siluer-Spoones, Rings, Gownes, Plate, or Linnen they haue loſt: ſome, to know how many Children they ſhall haue; ſome, how many Husbands, and which ſhall loue them beſt: others, about other buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; but in generall, all of them to know ſomething, which indeed at the laſt comes to nothing. And I my ſelfe (like a Holy-day foole) haue beene there at the leaſt halfe a ſcore times, onely to giue my money away, to bee laught at. Yet I haue words ynough: for he will promiſe more then twentie Courtiers, talke more for halfe a Peece then halfe a ſcore Lawyers, and lye more then twentie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12869:8"/>Chronologers: yet with ſome tricke, or euaſion, hee will come clearely off, without being ſuſpected for an Impoſtor, eſpecially if he haue ſome man in hand he thinkes he dare worke on, as he hath done me for example.</p>
            <p>For going to the Croſſe one Sunday morning to heare a Sermon,<note place="margin">Exordium.</note> ſome <hi>Mercurian</hi> and nimble-finger'd Pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocket, that had more minde of my Purſe then the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, gelt it of ſixteene pound; ſo that I went home ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by two Stone then I went out. After I had fretted much, and to no purpoſe, I vſed all the meanes I could to recouer my loſſe, as by feeing the Keepers of Newgate, who know which of that Law are appointed to filch in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery part of the Citie; yet ſtill I came home a greater loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer then I went out: for alwayes being in hope to finde that which I loſt, I loſt more, by bribing one Knaue, to diſcouer another. At the laſt, it was my bad fortune to meet with an old Woman, that put a greater confidence in the <hi>Iewes Caballs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bookes to tell Fortunes.</note> and <hi>Thalmud,</hi> the Shepheards Kalender, and Bookes of Palmiſtry, then any part of the Bible; who aduiſed me to repaire to Doctor <hi>P. C.</hi> in <hi>More-fields,</hi> at the vpper end of this Alley, and if Art could helpe me to it againe, I ſhould be ſure to heare of it. This draught of good newes this old Woman gaue me, to quench the thirſt of my deſire, which I dranke in at mine eares as greedily, as a man ſicke of a burning Feauer will the cooleſt Iulips: ſo giuing this old Piece of Superſtition a Teſter for her newes, I inſtantly went to Maſter Doctor. Who perceiuing me to be one that loued Gold well (becauſe Age moſt common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is couetous) thought the better to worke vpon me,<note place="margin">Auri ſura <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ames.</note> as he did: for his Doctorſhip had the Art to hold me in hand three weekes; in which time, he made the ſixteene pound I loſt, twentie: and when all came to a Period, hee told me, that he had laboured hard for me, and at the laſt, by his no ſmall induſtrie and paines, had found out the Theefe that had my Money, but he was fled into the <hi>Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> becauſe there were many Warrants out to apprehend
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12869:8"/>him for many Thefts and Burglaries hee had committed; and if it pleaſed me to take ſhipping, and ſayle thither, I ſhould be ſure to find him at the <hi>Labor in Vaine</hi> in <hi>Bredawe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Labor in Vaine.</note> But this comfort went as cold to my heart, as the Sentence of Death to a Man that ſtands arraigned at the Barre: for I had rather goe fiue thouſand mile by Land, then fiue mile by Sea; and if it had beene a hundred pound I had loſt, I would rather haue giuen as much more, then hazard my ſelfe by Water. Yet howſoeuer I may doubt, nay truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue my ſelfe; that he hath palpably cheated me: yet it was impoſſible to finde him a lyar, except I meant to take more paines about it, then it was worth. Therefore as patiently as I am able, I am going home againe, purpoſing hereafter to take heed of two Pick-pockets; the one, the Diuer that me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with me in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard; the other, the Doctor in <hi>More-fields,</hi> that rob'd me as well as the firſt, who in my mind hath deſerued, for his artificiall Cheating, the Pillory, as well as the other did the Gallowes, for Stealing.</p>
            <p>Thus Sir, according to my weake abilitie, haue I diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to you the condition of him, to whom theſe Women and my ſelfe come, the cauſe of our comming, with his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of deluding vs: for howſoeuer he profeſſeth himſelfe to haue an abſolute and exquiſite knowledge in Philoſophy, Aſtronomy, Phyſike, Metaphyſikes, the Mathematikes, and Aſtrology; yet if a Scholler had him in handling, he ſhould find him as meere a Mountebanke, as euer ſold Sophiſtica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in <hi>Italy</hi> or the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He no ſooner had deliuered me this Relation, but he haſted away from me: therefore ſeeing he was importunate to be gone, I only ſhew'd my ſelfe gratefull in thanking him for his kindneſſe; ſo he went homewards, &amp; I into my Garden. But now my minde was quite tranſported from the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that Place, and only fixt on the ſubtiltie of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, and his politike anſwer to the old Man about the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie of his Money; ſo that I could not be at quiet with my ſelfe, while I was truly reſolued of the Art of this Star-gazer.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12869:9"/>Therefore on a Morning which was as calme as I could wiſh my thoughts now were, I put on a Sute of courſe Northerne Dozens, with all account<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ements that were moſt ſutable to that homelineſſe, and with all expedition went to Maſter Doctor, and haſtily knocking at his Worſh ps doore, there came running downe the ſtayres with a nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dexteritie (the little <hi>Mephiſtophiles</hi>) his Boy, demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with whom I would ſpeake; to whom, in a broad <hi>Somerſetſhire</hi> language, I anſwered, with Maſter Doctor, vpon an earneſt buſineſſe. Vpon the deliuerie of this Meſſage, this young Spirit, like exhaled dew, nimbly flew away from me, who vpon an inſtant, like a flaſh of Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, was in my boſome againe before I could perceiue him; and then, without any more Interrogatories, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalled me vp into his Maſters Study, who ſat in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner following:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Figure-Caſter</note> Before a Square Table, couered with a greene Carpet, on which lay a huge Booke in <hi>Folio,</hi> wide open, full of ſtrange Characters, ſuch as the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> and <hi>Chaldaeans</hi> were neuer guiltie of;<note place="margin">His Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> not farre from that, a ſiluer Wand, a Surplus, a Watering Pot, with all the ſuperſtitious or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fayned Inſtruments of his couſening Art. And to put a fairer colour on his black and foule Science, on his head hee had a foure-cornered Cap, on his backe a faire Gowne (but made of a ſtrange f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſhion) in his right hand he held an Aſtrolabe, in his left a Mathematicall Glaſſe. At the firſt view, there was no man that came to him (if hee were of any faſhion) could offer him for his aduice leſſe then a <hi>Iacobus,</hi> and the meaneſt halfe a Peece, although hee peraduenture (rather then haue nothing) would be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a brace of Two-pences.</p>
            <p>I no ſooner came into his Study but I did him the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence belonging to his Doctorſhip, and ſtood as long bare to him, as a poore Countrey Client that ſues in <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Pauperi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> will to his hungry Lawyer. At the laſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with the expence of many a Legge (and may it pleaſe your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip)
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12869:9"/>I told him, that the cauſe of my comming was, that hauing lately loſt at the Kings Bench Barre in <hi>Westminster</hi> Hall a Chayne of Gold of three hundred Links, therefore I came to his Doctorſhip, hauing beene informed, that his Art could bring it to light againe: ſo putting my hand in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Leather Pouch, I greaſed his euer-dry Palmes with an Angell; who no ſooner had a feeling of my bountie, but hee began to be more liberall to mee of his Tongue, then I was to him of my Purſe: And while I ſtood leaning on my Staffe, hee deliuered this Emperike-like Oration in this or not much vnlike this manner.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Figure-Caſters Oration.</head>
               <p>HOneſt Friend, the loſſe you haue ſuſtayned, is ſo great, that I make no doubt, what you now haue giuen, or hereafter ſhall giue, will not come forced or wrackt from you, but voluntarie and free.<note place="margin">Nota.</note> For it is wiſdome in a Man to aduenture ſmall things to regayne greater, where there is a poſſibilitie of obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. He is not worthy of Money, that will not ſeeke after it, and he cannot truly iudge, how to value ſo preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Metall as Gold, that is not ſtung with the loſſe of it. Therefore Sir, your care deſerues a redreſſe, and this Booke (meaning his <hi>Ephimerides</hi>) with my Art and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie, ſhall be the Inſtrumentall Cauſes to make you happie in the recouerie of that which is worthie both of my Care and your Coſt. And to put you in ſome hope, if that Man that had your Chayne, liues eyther within the Horizon of <hi>England, Fraunce, Spaine, Italy,</hi> or the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> I will vndertake to ſhew you him, and in what place, and what companie hee is in. There is
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12869:10"/>not a Spirit, eyther of the Fire, Ayre, Earth, or Water, but I haue at my commaund as readily as any Gallant hath his Page or Foot-boy: I can coniure them all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and make them trot vp and downe the Citie, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing not a Pick-pockets, Gilts, Lifts, Decoyes, or Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Hoſe vnſurueyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Admi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anda jed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on credenda.</note>Looke here Sir (with that, hee aduanced his Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Glaſſe) with this Inſtrument, firſt deuiſed by that learned Man in our Art, <hi>Hermes Treſmegiſtus,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Mercurie,</hi> I can ſee all things done in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. If in the day time I looke in it, I will as eaſily ſee what is done in the Citie, as the Sunne. There can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not a withered-faced Lady paint her decayed Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance at her Chamber-Window, and ſet a faire gloſſe on it with her <hi>Fucuſſes</hi> and <hi>Italian</hi> Tinctures, but I ſee her as perfectly as her ſhee Secretarie her Chamber-maid. There cannot a Compter Booke-Keeper and a Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhare a poore Mans Fees, that the Night before was brought into Priſon (becauſe hee would not giue the blinking Beadle or begging Watch-man a Teſter) but I ſee it as eaſily as their fellow, the Bawd-like doore-keeper. There cannot a Iuſtices Clarke, that it may be is more Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice then his Maſter, take a Bribe of a noted Cut-purſe, whoſe Name peraduenture ſtands at leaſt twentie ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall times vpon record in <hi>Newgate</hi> Booke, but I perceiue it as well as the Doxye that brought it him.</p>
               <p>In the Night time, if I ſtand with this Inſtrument in my hand, I can ſee what is done in the Citie as well as the Man in the Moone. There cannot a Drunkard come reeling out of a Tauerne at twelue a Clocke at Night, but hee is as manifeſt before mee, as the Drawer that beat him out of doores after hee had ſpent all his Money. I can ſee the commaunding Conſtable and the drowſie Watch ſit nodding on a Stall, while a companie of Roaring-boyes, <hi>alias</hi> Brothers of the Sword, come by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12869:10"/>firſt ſwearing them awake, then out of their Authoritie, who in ſpight of their teeth will craue leaue to paſſe by them. There cannot a Tradeſ-mans Puritanicall Wife riſe early in a Morning, vnder the pretence of hearing a Lecture, but I know where ſhee goes as well as the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of her Shoppe that vſhers her. Nay Sir, I haue ſeene the Pope goe in his <hi>Pontificaelibus</hi> with his whole Heard of Cardinalls to Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Rome,</hi> as often as any Citizen hath ſeene the Right Honourable the Lord Maior goe to <hi>Pauls-Croſſe</hi> in <hi>London.</hi> As for <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Iacke,</hi> the Great <hi>Mogul,</hi> the Sophy of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and the Great Turke, I can ſee them as often as I doe my Boy, that is neuer from my elbow. And all this is done by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie, by ſacred Aſtrologie, Diuine Aſtrologie, the Art of Arts, the Science of Sciences, for it is the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, the moſt Authentike, the moſt excellent Art in the World. For old Father <hi>Adam</hi> was both an Aſtronomer and Aſtrologer; <hi>Abraham,</hi> and all the Patriarkes: Nay, I will aſſure you, the Students of our Art haue beene fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in all Countries;<note place="margin">Countries fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicians.</note> for <hi>Porphyrius</hi> and <hi>Apulcius</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riue the Originall of <hi>Magike</hi> from the <hi>Perſians,</hi> although <hi>Suidas</hi> will haue it from the <hi>Maguſeans,</hi> and from them hee calls them <hi>Magi;</hi> the <hi>Latines</hi> call vs Wiſe-men; the <hi>Grecians,</hi> Philoſophers; the <hi>Indians, Gymnoſophiſts;</hi> the <hi>Aegyptiant,</hi> Prieſts; the <hi>Cabaliſts,</hi> Prophets; the <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> and <hi>Aſſyrians, Chaldaeans;</hi> the <hi>Frenchmen, Bards:</hi> And many excellent and eminent Men haue flouriſhed in this Knowledge; as <hi>Zoroaſter,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Aromaſius,</hi> who laugh'd when hee was borne, among the <hi>Perſians;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mathematici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> 
                  <hi>Numa Pompilius,</hi> among the <hi>Romans; Thesbion,</hi> among the <hi>Gymnoſophiſts; Hermes,</hi> among the <hi>Aegyptians; Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> among the <hi>Babylonians; Zamolxis,</hi> among the <hi>Thra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians;</hi> and <hi>Abbaris,</hi> among the <hi>Hyperboreans.</hi> A thouſand more beſide theſe, were excellent Aſtrologers; as <hi>Ptho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomeus,</hi> whom ſome (though very fooles in their Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on)
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12869:11"/>hold to be the firſt Aſtronomer that euer was: then <hi>Meſſahala,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aſtronomers and Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</note> 
                  <hi>Aboaſar, Abenragel, Alchibichius, Albumazar, Abraham, Auenezra, Algazel, Hermes Treſmigiſtus, Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Higinus,</hi> and <hi>Thebit;</hi> after whom, did ariſe <hi>Maternus,</hi> that famous Mathematician: then, <hi>Georgius Purbachius;</hi> after whom, followed <hi>Iohannes de Monte Regio, Alphonſus</hi> King of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> as his Tables can teſtifie. Was not broad-ſhouldered <hi>Atlas,</hi> that was bigger then the great Porter, an admirable Aſtronomer and Aſtrologer? Was not * <hi>Erra Pater</hi> (whom I had almoſt forgot) a rare fellow at Aſtronomie?<note place="margin">Pater E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um.</note> Yes, as this his Table can teſtifie, which hee made I know not how many yeeres ſince, in an vnknowne Language; but now faithfully tranſlated into the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue by my ſelfe.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12869:11"/>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:12869:12"/>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <head>A TABLE MADE BY THE LEARNED ASTRONOMER <hi>ERRA PATER,</hi> ſhewing, that the Twelue Signes and Seuen Planets haue as great a Predomination ouer all Trades, and Callings, which <hi>are the Members of the Body of a Common-wealth, as ouer the Body of Man.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label"> </cell>
                        <cell role="label">♄ <hi>Saturne.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">♃ <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">♂ <hi>Mars.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">☉ <hi>Sol.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">♀ <hi>Venus.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">☿ <hi>Mercurie.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> 
                           <hi>Luna.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>♈ <hi>Aries.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Goldſmiths.</cell>
                        <cell>Haberdaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</cell>
                        <cell>Marchants.</cell>
                        <cell>Mercers.</cell>
                        <cell>Drapers.</cell>
                        <cell>Vintners.</cell>
                        <cell>Horners.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>♉ <hi>Taurus.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Butchers.</cell>
                        <cell>Graſiers.</cell>
                        <cell>Cookes.</cell>
                        <cell>Drugſters.</cell>
                        <cell>Tobacco men.</cell>
                        <cell>Players.</cell>
                        <cell>Fidlers.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>♊ <hi>Gemini.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Serieants.</cell>
                        <cell>Baylyes.</cell>
                        <cell>High-way men.</cell>
                        <cell>Lifts.</cell>
                        <cell>Cutpurſes.</cell>
                        <cell>Gilts.</cell>
                        <cell>Decoyes.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>♋ <hi>Cancer.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Brewers.</cell>
                        <cell>Dray-men.</cell>
                        <cell>Porters.</cell>
                        <cell>Tapſters.</cell>
                        <cell>Hoſtlers.</cell>
                        <cell>Conſtables.</cell>
                        <cell>Beadles.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>♌ <hi>Leo.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Roaring Boyes.</cell>
                        <cell>Young Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants.</cell>
                        <cell>Courtiers.</cell>
                        <cell>Cutlers.</cell>
                        <cell>Fencers.</cell>
                        <cell>Armorers.</cell>
                        <cell>Brothers of the Sword.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>♍ <hi>Virgo.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Sempſters.</cell>
                        <cell>Laundreſſes</cell>
                        <cell>Chamber-Maids.</cell>
                        <cell>Tyre-wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</cell>
                        <cell>Wayting Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women.</cell>
                        <cell>Flax-maids.</cell>
                        <cell>Tobacco Women.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>♎ <hi>Libra.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Grocers.</cell>
                        <cell>Chaundlors.</cell>
                        <cell>Cheeſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers.</cell>
                        <cell>Silke-men.</cell>
                        <cell>Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</cell>
                        <cell>Pewterers.</cell>
                        <cell>Plummers.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>♏ <hi>Scorpio.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Vſurers.</cell>
                        <cell>Brokers.</cell>
                        <cell>Informers.</cell>
                        <cell>Promooters.</cell>
                        <cell>Petty-fog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</cell>
                        <cell>Sumners.</cell>
                        <cell>Iaylors.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>♐ <hi>Sagittarius.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Fletchers.</cell>
                        <cell>Gunners.</cell>
                        <cell>Scriueners.</cell>
                        <cell>Smiths.</cell>
                        <cell>Braſiers.</cell>
                        <cell>Iron-mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</cell>
                        <cell>Turners.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>♑ <hi>Capricornus</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Drugſters.</cell>
                        <cell>Milliners.</cell>
                        <cell>Coach-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</cell>
                        <cell>Iewellers.</cell>
                        <cell>Stone-Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</cell>
                        <cell>Painters.</cell>
                        <cell>Shoomakers</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>♒ <hi>Aquarius.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Watermen.</cell>
                        <cell>Water-bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.</cell>
                        <cell>Cloth-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</cell>
                        <cell>Bakers.</cell>
                        <cell>Salters.</cell>
                        <cell>Sadlers.</cell>
                        <cell>Barbars.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>♓ <hi>Piſces.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Oyſter-Wiues.</cell>
                        <cell>Fiſh-mong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</cell>
                        <cell>Fruiterers.</cell>
                        <cell>Hoſiers.</cell>
                        <cell>Gold-find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</cell>
                        <cell>Taylors.</cell>
                        <cell>Plaſterers.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:12869:13"/>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:12869:13"/>
               <head>A Heauenly Oration.</head>
               <p>VVHat thinke you Sir, was not this learned Artiſt deepely read in the large-leau'd Booke of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen? Doe not you thinke hee could learnedly diſcourſe of the Poles, Spheres, Orbes, Circumferences, Circles, Centres, Diameters, the Zodiake, the Zenith, the Artike and Antartike Poles, <hi>Tropicus Capricorni,</hi> and <hi>Tropicus Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cri?</hi> Hee was as well acquainted with the Twelue Signes in Heauen, as any Tradeſ-man with thoſe in <hi>Cheape-ſide,</hi> and runne ouer the Nature of the Seuen Planets as nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly as the <hi>French</hi> Vaulter ouer the Ropes. And I my ſelfe,<note place="margin">Margarita Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophica de principiis Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomiae, <hi>Lib. 7. tract. 1. cap. 7.</hi>
                  </note> (but that I know this kind of Learning is out of your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lement)could diſcourſe to you what a ſullen fellow <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> is (on whom the permanent continuation of all things depend) what a iouiall fellow <hi>Iupiter</hi> (on whom the fecunditie of Agent Cauſes relye) what a quarrelling Swaſh-buckler <hi>Mars</hi> (on whom the ſwift expedition of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing to the effect doth hang) what a hot fellow <hi>Sol</hi> (whom all Agent Cauſes follow) what a wanton Wench <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> (on whom the fecunditie of all Materiall Cauſes looke after) what a merry fellow <hi>Mercury</hi> (in whom a manifold vertue doth flouriſh) and what a madde Laſſe <hi>Luna</hi> (on whom the encreaſe and decreaſe of Humane things conſiſt.) For know, that the rich and golden Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt that I haue gathered out of the ſweete and fruitfull Fields of many Learned Mens Workes, and carefully hoorded vp in the Garner of my breſt, hath made me full and copious in my Knowledge; ſo that there is no Art and Science, but I am as deepely and profoundly read in, as thoſe that haue taken the Worſhipfull Degree of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor. I am ſo good at Phyſike, that euery Morning I haue whole troupes of Mad-men, and others, ſicke of <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pegoes, Gouts, Epilepſies, Feuers,</hi> and many others labouring vnder as dangerous Diſeaſes as theſe, ſend their Vrine to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12869:14"/>me, ſo that neuer Doctor was ſo famous: for when Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine will not preuayle,<note place="margin">Phyſitions.</note> and that neyther <hi>Galen, Paracel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, Auecin, Hippocrates,</hi> nor all the Heires of <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> can cure them; I haue a Spirit that will fright any diſeaſe from the moſt dangerous and ouer-ſpent Patient. My skill in Alchymie is ſo great, that I can turne any thing that is brought to me into as perfect Gold as euer came out of the <hi>Indies.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Alchymiſts.</note> Frier <hi>Bacon</hi> was an Aſſe, Doctor <hi>Faustus</hi> a Foole, <hi>Ripley</hi> an Empericke, and <hi>Kelly</hi> a Coxcombe to me; they were not worthy to blow my Bellowes, or looke to my Stylls, while I worke for the Philoſophers Stone. But for Aſtrologie, I can doe that none of my Profeſſion, beſides my ſelfe, could euer reach vnto: for there is nothing loſt, but I can finde againe; nothing in hazard of loſing, but I can preſerue ſafe and ſure; I haue giuen Tradeſ-men Spirits, that haue kept their Shops as faithfully, as if they had twentie Iourneymen continually in it. There is not a part of the Body, but I can giue a Spirit to keepe it ſafe and ſound.</p>
               <p>Therefore Sir, to conclude, aſſure your ſelfe, that if all my Spirits and mine owne endeuours can doe you a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure (as you need not doubt of mine Art) you ſhall not faile of your Chayne: ſo merrily returne to your Lodging againe, and repayre to mee to morrow Morning, thirtie Minutes after ſix; and alwayes remember to admire at the wonderfull power of Sacred, Diuine, and Heauenly Aſtrologie.</p>
               <p>When hee had made an end of almoſt his endleſſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, wherewith he had ſo bejaded and tyred mine eares, I was as glad as any young Dottrell, that had made an eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape from the clawes of the Puttock-like Catch-poles. A ſicke Man, that is troubled with the tedious impertinent diſcourſe of a prating Nurſe, could not be more happy at her ſilence, then I at his; for I was in doubt, that his volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12869:14"/>Tongue being once on the Wheele, would neuer haue left running. The Mountebanks Drug Tongue, the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers bumbaſted Tongue, the <hi>Gypſies</hi> Canting Tongue,<note place="margin">Strange Tongues.</note> the Lawyers <hi>French</hi> Tongue, the <hi>Welch</hi> Tongue; nay, all the Tongues that were at the fall of <hi>Babylon</hi> (when they were all confuſedly mingled together) could as well be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood as his ſtrange Tongue: ſo that if I had beene but as ignorant as he tooke me to be (ſuppoſing, that I did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend what did belong to his learned Art of Couſenage) he would haue made me beleeue, that his worth was corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent to his words. At the laſt recouering my ſelfe (for hee had almoſt talk'd me out of my Wits) I heartily thanked him; firſt, for his learned Diſcourſe; ſecondly, for his Comfort; and thirdly, and as ſpeedily as I could, made him this Anſwer, which I hope will proue as great a terror to all Figure-Caſters, as <hi>Newgate</hi> to Cut-purſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Anſwer to the Figure-Caſter, and the <hi>Confutation of it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SIr, if you euery day ſhould trouble your ſelfe, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe that heare you, with theſe long-winded Exerciſes, you had need eate great ſtore of Lycoris: and if you lye ſo much to euery man, as you haue done to me, you had beſt learne of <hi>Symonides</hi> the Art of Memory; for theſe two things are moſt requiſite for thoſe that talke and lye ſo much as you doe. You haue made a large Aſtrologicall diſcourſe, only to make me a Foole, and proue your ſelfe a Knaue; for cunningly in your <hi>Exordium</hi> you hearten me on to cheat my ſelfe: for doth not a man palpably couſen himſelfe, when he giues money to a Knaue, that firſt cheats him before his face, then laughs at him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind his backe; which is the true cuſtome of all Figure-Caſters, of whoſe facultie you profeſſe to be.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:12869:15"/>
               <p>As for your Inſtruments, as your Mathematicall Glaſſe, with which you can doe wonders, your Siluer Wand, Watering Pot, foure-corner'd Cap, are but meere ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Ornaments, either borrowed from the <hi>Iewes</hi> or <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</hi> And it is a queſtion,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Koia.</hi> The Papiſts meere Coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere.</note> whether the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſts had theſe from the Roguiſh Coniurers, or the Coniurers from them: for iuſt ſuch Ceremonies and Exorciſmes the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurers vſe vpon their inuocation of Deuills, the Papiſts doe in their inuocations; for they exorciſe and coniure their Salt, that it may not loſe the ſauour, and their Water, which the ignorant people gape for as greedily as a Rauen will for coole ayre in the midſt of Iuly, and this they call * Holy Water:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>otius aqua ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>dista.</note> then they coniure their Oyle, their Balme, their Hearbes, and Plants, that they may haue the vertue and influence to heale the ſicke and diſeaſed: they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure their Candles, that they may not burne blew; and Bees, that they proſper, and not ſting any Holy or Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Frier, when hee dares aduenture his bald Crowne nigh one of their Hyues. What is their Chriſtening of Bells, Altars, Pilgrimages, Proceſſions, Images, Holy-Aſhes, Holy-Pace-Egges, Flames, Palmes, and Palme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boughes, Albes, Copes, and Maniples, Veſtiments, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Staues, Fooles, and Fryers Hoods, Shells, and Bells, Paxes, licking of rotten Bones, creeping to Woodden Images and Croſſes, ſhauing of Crownes, and a thouſand of the like Antike Trickes, but flat Sorcerie and Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft?</p>
               <p>And doe not all theſe Fooleries agree with the Coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers Rogueries? Who alwayes obſerue the Time of the Moone before they ſet their Figure, and when they haue ſet their Figure, and ſpread their Circle, firſt exorciſe the Wine and Water which they ſprinkle on their Circle, then mumble in an vnknowne Language: Doe they not croſſe and exorciſe their Surplus, their Siluer Wand, Gowne, Cap, and euery Inſtrument they vſe about their blacke and damnable Art? Nay, they croſſe the place
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12869:15"/>whereon they ſtand, becauſe they thinke the Deuill hath no power to come into it, when they haue bleſt it: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I cannot be perſwaded, but you had your Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies from the Papiſts, who firſt had them from the <hi>Iewes</hi> or <hi>Pagans,</hi> or they from you, for you both couſen the poore blinded people after one manner; firſt, of their Soules, by drawing them to Superſtition; ſecondly, of their Eſtates, by defrauding them of their Money: for which cauſe, both of you haue deuiſed theſe Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</p>
               <p>Thus much for your Inſtruments. Now for your Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors you pile vp on the necke of each other, I hold not lawfull to be ſtudied to an ill intent; and for moſt of them, I hold Atheiſts, and fellowes, whoſe Workes ought rather to be burnt, for being ſtuft full of Blaſphemy, then to be read for our inſtruction, or knowledge, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after I will ſhew you. As for <hi>Adam, Abraham,</hi> or any of the Twelue Patriarkes skill in Coniuration, Figure-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, or rayſing a Spirit, as you ſay, I am ſure they practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed none.</p>
               <p>And for your knowledge in Aſtronomie,<note place="margin">Aſtronomie.</note> this is my opinion of you, that you haue as much skill of the Poles in Heauen, as you haue of the Poles on <hi>Pauls</hi> Steeple.</p>
               <p>Your skill in Phyſike ſhall by no meanes make me (if I chance to fall ſicke) chuſe you for my Doctor,<note place="margin">Phyſike.</note> except I am wearie of my life; for I ſhall be in more danger of death by taking your Potions, then I ſhall be of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe. But indeed, for a Man that deſires preſent Cure, I thinke you are excellent for, becauſe I make no doubt, that you will hold him long in hand: and in this you and all other <hi>Medicaſters</hi> and Dog-leaches are happy, becauſe the Sunne doth alwayes behold your good ſucceſſe, and the Earth couers all your ignorances.<note place="margin">Pli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>29.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> Talis Medi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> eſt Ded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us.</note> It is a common ſaying, <hi>Nullum Medicum eſſe peritum niſi triginta homines ad orcum dimiſerit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> That it is impoſſible for any Phyſition
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:12869:16"/>to be skilfull, except hee hath killed his thirtie men. But for your part I dare ſweare, if you ſhould kill three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred (as it may be it comes ſomething nigh that number, becauſe you haue beene a long practitioner) you would ſtill remaine but a Quack-ſaluing Phyſician; one, that it may be hath ſome little faint glimmering of the Practicke, but nothing of the Theorie of this moſt learned and deepe Art:<note place="margin">Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> For beeing ſo illiterate as you are, how can you, (neyther vnderſtanding the Greeke or Latine Tongues, in which the grounds of Phyſike were firſt writ) bee ſo famous as you report your ſelfe to be? Yet there is one thing in your large Oration, that would make a Man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue you haue ſome skill in Phyſike, becauſe you ſay, that whole Troupes of Mad-men come to you: in this a Man may beleeue you, for if Men were not madde, and ſtarke out of their Wits, they would neuer come to you for your aduice.</p>
               <p>There is nothing you haue ſpoken, that I can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade my ſelfe you haue ſaid true,<note place="margin">Alchymi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> but in this, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing your ſelfe an Alchymiſt: for I dare vndertake, that if a Man bring you a Cart-Load of Braſſe, Iron, or Pewter, you can, in the time a Man will goe eyther into <hi>Long-Lane,</hi> or <hi>Houndſ-Ditch,</hi> turne it into as good Gold, as is in the richeſt Vſurers cloſe-ſhut Powch in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie. But for the Philoſophers Stone, I thinke you can finde out the Quadrature of the Circle, or a new way to the <hi>Eaſt-Indies,</hi> as ſoone as finde out that: if you can finde it out for others, why cannot you as well for your ſelues?</p>
               <p>By this, a Man may perceiue the Roguerie of all Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chymiſts, and the true nature of their Art, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is an Art without Art, whoſe beginning is, ſtoutly to lye,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ns,</note> and whoſe end is, miſerably to begge. And to conclude, all theſe Gold-engendring <hi>Chymiſts,</hi> are <hi>Archy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists,</hi> rather <hi>Lechymists,</hi> and make all thoſe that follow them, <hi>Lachrymiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:12869:16"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Flyes and Spirits.</note>For your Art, in giuing Men Flyes and Spirits to expell all ill lucke from them; I thinke it is as eaſie to bee done, and to as much purpoſe, as the Licence and Power Pope <hi>Paul</hi> the third gaue to <hi>Serona Marta Oſori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and twelue of her Bloud, who by the vertue of a payre of coniured Beads, could be forgiuen the third part of their ſinnes, if they ſaid but one <hi>Pater-Noſter,</hi> although it was ſaid without Deuotion.</p>
               <p>Alſo your Spirits for all Trades, and to cure all Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, and to defend euery part of the Body, is as prettie and quaint a Deceit, as that of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion; who will ſell any Vocation a Saint, to keepe, defend, and proſper it: For they hold, that Saint <hi>Hugh</hi> and Saint <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtace</hi> guard Hunters from Perills and Dangers, that the Stagge or Bucke may not hit them on the Head with their Hornes; Saint <hi>Martin</hi> and Saint <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> guard all Ale-Knights, Tauerne-Hunters, and Drunkards, from falling into the Kennell, as they goe reeling to their Lodgings; Saint <hi>Chrispine</hi> and <hi>Chrispinus</hi> defend all Shoo-makers; Saint <hi>Arnold</hi> preſerues Millers; Saint <hi>Stephen,</hi> Weauers.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Saints for Cattell.</note>They haue Saints alſo for Cattell: as, Saint <hi>Anthonie</hi> for Hogges, Saint <hi>Loy</hi> for Horſe and Kine, Saint <hi>Gallus</hi> for Geeſe, Saint <hi>Wendelin</hi> for Sheepe; and Saint <hi>Gertrude</hi> poyſoneth all Rats and Mice: ſo that none of theſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine were euer knowne to gnaw any Fryers Cheeſe or Bacon.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Saints for Diſeaſes.</note>For Diſeaſes, they hold, that Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> and Saint <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentine</hi> keepe Men, eſpecially Women, from the Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-ſickneſſe: that Saint <hi>Anthonie</hi> heales all kinde of Fires, though they be as hot as euer came out of any <hi>French</hi> Hoſpitall: Saint <hi>Roch</hi> the Peſtilence; and that's the cauſe (they ſay) ſo few of them dyed the laſt great Plague-time: Saint <hi>Roman</hi> reſtores all Mad people to their Wits; Saint <hi>Iob</hi> is good for the Pocks; Saint <hi>Appolin</hi> is as good at the Tooth-ach.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:12869:17"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Saints <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> part of the Body.</note>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> for euery Limbe in M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they haue a Saint: for S. <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>a</hi> keepes the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d, in ſtead of <hi>Aries; S. Blaſius</hi> is appo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ted to goue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e the Necke, in ſtead of <hi>Taurus;</hi> S. <hi>Lawr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce</hi> keepes the Backe and Shoulders, in ſtead of <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m, Cancer,</hi> and <hi>Leo; S. Eraſmus</hi> rules the Belly, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntrayles, in the place of <hi>Libra</hi> and <hi>Scorpius:</hi> in the ſtead of <hi>Sagittarius, Capricornus, Aquarius,</hi> and <hi>Piſces,</hi> the Holy Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath elected S. <hi>Burgarde,</hi> S. <hi>Rochus,</hi> S. <hi>Quirinus,</hi> S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> and many others, which gouerne the Thighes, Feet, Shinnes and Knees.</p>
               <p>All theſe things being truly conſidered, I admire there are ſo many Tradeſmen breake<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo many great rich men dye, and ſo many Sickneſſes and Diſeaſes in <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> ſeeing their Saints haue ſuch power to driue theirs away, and our Cunning Men and Women ſo many Charmes to fright away ours. But ſure, if theſe things were true, Doctors, Apothecaries, and Chirurgians would be as poore as Fidlers, Poets, and Alchymiſts. But I will giue as much credit to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Saints, as to our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Mountebanks Spirits, which were firſt inuented by ſubtill Fryers and craftie Knaues, only to beguile the poore people of their Money.</p>
               <p>It may be (Sir) at the firſt you ſuppoſed me to be (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of my plaine Countrey Habit) a Woodcocke fit for your Sprindge: but to be plaine with you Sir, your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is deceiued of me, for I can perceiue you to be an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Knaue; for your trickes are ſo thin and ſleight, that a Man of a very dim vnderſtanding may ſee cleane through them. Your diſcourſe is neyther knit together with the Nerues of Vnderſtanding, Wit, Art, Iudgement, or Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it hath no Realitie or Eſſence in it: but you huddle a companie of Aſtronomicall words together, wanting both Coherence, Methode, and Congruitie; you powre out whole Dictionaries of ſtrange Words, talke as though you could repeat <hi>Dutch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Gallobelgicus</hi> or <hi>Engliſh Hollings-head</hi> without booke,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>pulent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and lye as if you had held <hi>Herodotus</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:12869:17"/>Penne while hee writ the Nine Muſes. To tell you true Sir, I came not hither to find out a Chayne (for indeede I haue loſt none) but firſt to find out, then to expreſſe your Roguerie: therefore I thinke, if you had beene a true Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, it were impoſſible I ſhould put a Tricke vpon you, that is ſo excellent at the moſt Couſening, Cheating, and Conycatching Art of Aſtrologie.</p>
               <p>I perceiue by your ſweating, I am very tedious to you: but good Sir be patient, for I haue giuen your Tongue an vncontroulable libertie, to ſpeake in the defence of your Art, that hath been ſo beneficiall to you: therefore I hope you will giue me leaue (if not, I now will be ſo bold as to take it) to ſpeake in the diſprayſe of it, becauſe it hath beene ſo preiudiciall to many.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ordo praepoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus. Confutatio vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garis.</note>If Figure-Caſting be an Art, or Science, why is it not a Liberall Science as well as all the other? or why is it not ſtudied as freely and as lawfully as the reſt, but that the Profeſſor of it is forced to flye into ſuch by places, darke Corners, and Garden-Allyes, as theſe? If you are aſhamed to ſhew the reaſons, I will not, but truely reueale them; which are, either becauſe the generall eye of the world may not take notice of the foolery of thoſe people, and ſo giue them warning, or that the roguery of you that entice them may not be apparant, and ſo you come to a deſerued pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment: Or that you may bee thought more famous in the opinion of the ignorant, who ſuppoſe that ſuch melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly places beſt ſuite with ſuch as ſtudy theſe Arts.<note place="margin">Figure-Caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Cunning Men, and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> This may appeare by the cunning Man on the <hi>Bank-ſide,</hi> Mother <hi>Broughton</hi> in <hi>Chicke-Lane,</hi> yong Maſter <hi>Oliue</hi> in <hi>Turnebole-ſtreet,</hi> the ſhag-hair'd Wizard in <hi>Pepper-Alley,</hi> the Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion with the Bag-pipe Cheeke, Doctor <hi>Fore-man</hi> at <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth,</hi> and you here in <hi>More-fields,</hi> and many ſuch Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, that like the Birds of Wonder flye the light of the Citie.</p>
               <p>Againe, there is no Art or Science, but the definition ſhewes the excellencie of it.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:12869:18"/>
               <p>Grammar is the Science of ſpeaking and writing truly,<note place="margin">Grammar.</note> the Fountaine and Originall of all Arts.</p>
               <p>Logicke the Art of Arts,<note place="margin">Logicke.</note> the Science of Sciences, that makes way for the beginning of all Methodes, and an Art that by diſputing finds out the Truth.</p>
               <p>Rhetoricke is an Art,<note place="margin">Rhetoricke.</note> teaching to ſpeake elegantly, by Tropes and Figures.</p>
               <p>Arithmaticke is the Doctrine of Numbers.<note place="margin">Arithmaticke.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Muſicke the harmonious facultie of weighing the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of Sounds by Sence and Reaſon.<note place="margin">Muſicke.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Geometrie the Diſcipline of Immoueable Greatneſſes,<note place="margin">Geometrie.</note> and the contemplatiue deſcription of Formes.</p>
               <p>Aſtronomie a certaine Law and Rule,<note place="margin">Aſtronomie.</note> conſidering the Motion of Superior Bodyes.</p>
               <p>Philoſophie the knowledge of Diuine and Humane things<note place="margin">Philoſophie.</note> ioyned with the ſtudie of liuing well.</p>
               <p>Phyſicke the Art of curing and healing the ſicke and diſeaſed.<note place="margin">Phyſicke.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But for your Aſtrologie, your Sacred Aſtrologie, your Diuine Aſtrologie, I neuer read, that any Diuine, Father, or Preacher euer gaue any commendable deſcription of it: Indeed, ſome of that wiſe Sect you profeſſe your ſelfe to be of, haue endeuoured to illuſtrate and beautifie, with one of whoſe Authoritie I will not allow of, becauſe Diuinitie (the Queene and Miſtreſſe of the Arts) doth deny it. Therefore, becauſe there is no true deſcription of this Art, if the Students of it will thinke themſelues beholding to me, I will furniſh them with one.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A new and true deſcription of Aſtrologie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AStrologie i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> an Art, whereby Cunning Knaues cheat plaine honeſt Men, that teacheth both the Theory and Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke of cloſe Couſenage, a Science inſtructing all the Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents of it to lye as often as they ſpeake, and to be beleeued no
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12869:18"/>oftner then they hold their Tongues; that tells truth as often as Bawds goe to Church, Witches or Whores ſay their Prayers, or neuer but when the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Nones and the</hi> Greeke <hi>Calends meet together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the true deſcription of your Art. Now the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and power of your Art, is to calculate Deaths and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuities, caſt Figures, finde out things that it may be were neuer loſt, giue Fooles Flyes to win if they can at Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and more of the like, which I will not nominate, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it will be troubleſome to my ſelfe, and tedious to your Doctorſhip (whom I perceiue to be as full of Frets, as a Muſician) all which I will proue to be vnlawfull, to the diſgrace of all the damnable and diabolicall Students in that Art; and if I doe not artificially confute and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found all thoſe that can rayſe a Spirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and caſt a Figure, and all other Mountebankes, Emperickes, and Impoſtors, ſuch as you are that pretend to doe it; then let them boldly and confidently ſay, I am but a meere Freſh-man, and no true Maſter in my Art.</p>
               <p>Some Principles, conducing to the perfect Science and Knowledge of Aſtrologie, handle the Natures and the Parts of the Zodiake; others, the Qualities of the Planets; ſome, the Dimenſions and abſtruſe ſignifications of the Houſes. The Aſtrologers themſelues diuide the Zodiake into twelue Parts or Signes, hauing euery part conſiſting of thirtie degrees of Longitude, and twelue of Latitude. In theſe prettie Inuentions they ſhew themſelues Poets as well as Aſtrologers, in fayning ſo neatly: for can any of them make me beleeue there are Twelue Signes to bee ſeene in Heauen as viſibly as thoſe on the Earth,<note place="margin">Aſtrologers make a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe in Heauen.</note> or that there are any ſuch Creatures in Heauen, as the crooke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn'd Ram, the goring Bull, the poyſon-ſpitting Scorpion, any lecherous Crab-fiſh, vnconſcionable Scales,<note place="margin">Lege Margari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam Philoſophi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cam de princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n cap. <hi>23<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> &amp; cap. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> roaring Lyon, or hot-rayned Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t? Can any of you make me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue there is ſuch a Wilderneſſe of wild Beaſts as theſe?
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12869:19"/>it may be indeede there is <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgo,</hi> becauſe ſhee is ſeldome ſeene on the Earth;<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſa maior &amp; nanor. Canis ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or &amp; Cani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ula. Drago. Vultur. Anguis. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pus &amp; Ca.</note> but for the angry Beare, ſnarling Dogge, venomous Dragon, greedie Vultur, hiſſing Snake, horrible <hi>Hydra,</hi> fearefull Haire, or Man-louing Dolphin to be in Heauen, I neuer will beleeue it: howſoeuer I haue heard a plaine Countrey fellow ſtand in defence of it, that if there were no ſuch things in Heauen, ſuch Wiſe-men as Almanack-Makers would neuer put them forth in Print. But I will laugh at their ignorance, and ſcoffe at all Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-wiſe Wizards with <hi>Bion</hi> the Philoſopher,<note place="margin">Bion.</note> that held thoſe Aſtronomers and Aſtrologers ridiculous, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee Fiſhes ſwim in the Sea, yet affirme they haue ſeene them in Heauen:<note place="margin">Diogenes.</note> Or deride them, as <hi>Diogenes</hi> did; who ſeeing an Aſtrologer offer a Table to ſell, whereon was painted the Errant Starres,<note place="margin">Lege Lucia.</note> ſaid to him: Sure thou art de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued good fellow, they are not the Starres that erre, but thou that ſelleſt them; biting at the folly of theſe Calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators, that moſt commonly erre in their Opinions.</p>
               <p>The ſame Philoſopher hearing a Starre-catcher make a long, and (as hee thought) a learned diſcourſe about the Celeſtiall Signes, askt him if he euer were there, hee knew them ſo well, or euer had any hope to come thither, he did lye ſo much? for is it poſſible (ſaith he) that you can truly know what is in Heauen, or what is done there, when in your abſence, you cannot ſee or know what is done at home? But theſe are onely Ieſts put vpon them, not Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to confute them: but I will proue there are no ſuch things in Heauen as theſe they talke, and ſhew the reaſon why they faine ſuch things to be in Heauen.</p>
               <p>As the diuerſities of the Circles deſcribed in the Spheres are meerely imaginarie;<note place="margin">Note.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">The diuiſion of the Zodiake meerely ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginatie, not naturall.</note> ſo the diuiſion of the Zodiake is not materiall, or of the firſt Creation, but onely fayned by the will and arbitrement of the Aſtrologers, that thereby they may know the Beginnings and the End of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens Motion. And the reaſon that they diuide the Zodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ake into Twelue Signes, neither more or leſſe, and that
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12869:19"/>euery Signe is diuided into thirtie Degrees, and euery De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree into ſixtie Minutes; is becauſe this Number is moſt fit for Calculations, as the Aſtrologers themſelues do wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: as <hi>Hales Auenradon</hi> on the expoſition of <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> and <hi>Abrabam Auenozra</hi> in his Booke of Aſtrologicall Reaſons, <note>plce="marg" Hales Auenra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</note> ſo that they might, if it had pleaſed them, haue diuided the Zodiacke into more or fewer parts, but they would not: which diuiſion is cleane contrary to the Doctrine of the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> for they teach,<note place="margin">Caldeans.</note> that there are not Twelue Signes but Eleuen Images, ſo couple Libra and Scorpio tege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>A man cannot alledge a ſtronger reaſon not to beleeue theſe Aſtrologers and Artleſſe Empericks, then the ſtrange opinions they hold, and to heare how ſtoutly moſt of them will defend the groſſe abſurdities of many Philoſophers and Aſtronomers: For doe you not thinke <hi>Eudoxus</hi> and and <hi>Aratus</hi> were mad when they would boldly affirme,<note place="margin">Aug. de Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Dei.</note> that they knew how many ſtarres were in Heauen, and the Names and Operation of them all? Were not the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Aſtronomers out of their wits, that held the ſtarres were ſtucke on the roofe of Heauen, no otherwiſe then Artificiall ſtarres on the top of ſome ſumptuous building? Was it not a fondneſſe in that Epieure, that did certainely beleeue, that when the ſtarres did ſhine in the night that then they were but kindled of God, and when they did vaniſh away, by the approch of the day, that then they were quencht by him? as if we ſhould ſay, when wee ſee a man, then he is borne; but when he is out of our ſight, then he is dead.<note place="margin">Origen lib. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> What an Abſurditie was it in <hi>Origen</hi> to affirme that the Sunne and the Moone, and the reſt of the ſtarres, were liuing creatures,<note place="margin">Lactant confu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> hanc opinionem. in lib. <hi>1.</hi> Inſt c. <hi>5</hi>
                  </note> being capable both of our Vices and Vertues? grounding his weake argument vpon the words of <hi>Iob,</hi> who ſayde; That the Starres were not Pure in the ſight of God: which was not meant, or ſpoken, as they were Rationable Creatures, but as they were glorious ſtarres, and of a moſt excellent and full brightneſſe, who although they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12869:20"/>were neuer ſo tralucent and bright, yet they were but dim in the ſight of their Maker. Therefore in my mind, what Aſtrologers or Aſtronomers ſoeuer they be, that thinkes Starres rationable Creatures, are worthy to be accounted moſt vnreaſonable and ſenſeleſſe themſelues.</p>
               <p>What a Vanitie was it in that Aſtronomer, that held, that Starres had their Motion from themſelues? which is moſt abſurd: for if a Starre is moued by it ſelfe, then Nature is defectiue, which neuer gaue any Figure or Organ to any Starre for ſuch a Motion. But Nature neuer was defectiue in any thing,<note place="margin">Motas Stella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> doth not abound in ſuperfluous things, or doth any thing in vaine: Therefore we muſt conclude, no Starre hath the Motion from it ſelfe, but hath it from God, that is the true Prime Moter all the wiſe and learned Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers haue ſo much talked of.</p>
               <p>What an error is it in ſome againe, that doubt whether the World be Sphericall, or round, or not? which doubt is moſt vaine and idle: for this ſenſible World was made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the example and ſimilitude of the Intellectuall, the Arch Type and Idea of the Diuine Minde; in which is neyther Beginning nor End,<note place="margin">Boetius, de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lat. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Plato, &amp; Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curius Triſme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtus.</note> ſuch as you may perceiue in a Sphericall Figure. Againe, it may be argued Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally thus, That it is a fit thing for that Body that containes within it all things, ſhould haue the moſt capable Figure, which is the Sphericall.</p>
               <p>What an abſurditie was it in <hi>Plato</hi> (the Diuineſt Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher and greateſt ſearcher of Nature that euer writ) to hold, that after the full reſolution of thirtie thouſand yeeres,<note place="margin">Magnus Annus Platonis. In Margarita Philoſophica poſt reuolutionem <hi>49000</hi> Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Polyd. Virg lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi> de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ant. one.</note> all things ſhould returne againe to the firſt ſtate and condition they were at in the Non-age and Infancie of the World? If this were true, then our firſt Father ſhould be placed once more in <hi>Paradice,</hi> once againe ſhould the Serpent tempt <hi>Eue,</hi> and once more ſhould Chriſt be crucified, &amp; riſe again: then ſhould all thoſe bleſt Soules that are in Heauen, liue on the Earth againe, and all they that are in Hell, be freed from their torments. But Diuinitie proues all this to be falſe.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:12869:20"/>
               <p>Was it not a great ouerſight in <hi>Cicero, Plato,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Philoſophers to beleeue,<note place="margin">The chiming of the Spheres. <hi>Ambro. lib.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that there is Muſical conſent and ſound wrought by the ordinary Motion of the Starres and Planets? which cannot be: for the celeſtiall &amp; ſuperior part of Heauen hath no Aire in it, without which there can be no ſound made; neither do celeſtiall Bodies, while they moue in their Spheres, touch any hard or harſh thing, as the finger doth the Lute or Harpe, which is the cauſe of ſuch Muſicall and Harmonious Raptures.</p>
               <p>Alſo to what purpoſe was it in many Writers, to hold a difference whereabout the Middle of the Earth ſhould be? The ancienteſt Writers hold that it was at <hi>Delphos:</hi> vpon which occaſion <hi>Strabo</hi> doth declare a Fable,<note place="margin">Strabo.</note> how that there were two Eagles ſent forth by <hi>loue,</hi> one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Eaſt, another from the Weſt, both which came to <hi>Delphos,</hi> to a place call'd <hi>Omphalo,</hi> that is <hi>Vmbiculo,</hi> the Nauell: but this is fabulous, therfore vaine Many Coſmographers &amp; Aſtronomers hold that the Centre of the Earth is either in Mount <hi>Taurus,</hi> hard by <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> where they report the Ark ſtood, or in the field <hi>Semiaar,</hi> or in ſome other place of <hi>Meſopotamia.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ptolomey.</note> 
                  <hi>Ptolomy</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeues it was placed vnder the Aequinoctiall Circle. <hi>Strabo</hi> ſayth, it was in <hi>Pernaſſus,</hi> a Mountaine in <hi>Greece:</hi> to which, <hi>Plutarch</hi> and others agree.<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> But I will not credit the beſt of theſe (although it be a matter of no great conſequence) but inquire among the learned Fathers, and ſeeke out the truth from them many of whom beleeue &amp; report, that the middle of the Earth is in <hi>Iudea,</hi> &amp; eſpecially <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to be the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre: of which opinion is <hi>Lyra, Hylarius,</hi> &amp; many others,<note place="margin">Iyra. Hylarius.</note> who moſt confidently beleeue it, becauſe they alledge the ſaying of the Prophet,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 74.</note> 
                  <hi>Deus operatus eſt ſalutem in medio terrae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is it not as groſſe in many Geographers &amp; Aſtronomers, to argue with forcible reaſons,<note place="margin">Verſipodes.</note> that iuſt vnderneath this habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble world there is another beyond the Ocean, in which peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple liue whoſe feet are oppoſit to ours? which opinion ſeem'd ſtrange both to <hi>Lactantius</hi> &amp; S. <hi>Aug.</hi> and I cannot chuſe but admire at their confidence in it: for if they argue thus,<note place="margin">Lactant. Inſtitut. lib <hi>3</hi> cap. <hi>24.</hi> Auguſtin. de Ciu. Dei. li b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> why
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:12869:21"/>doe they not argue this concerning the Water and the Earth, which by this meanes is no leſſe pendant and hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then the body of man: For if a man looke on the ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation of the Heauen &amp; Earth, the Antipodites haue their feete downewards and their heads vpwards as well as wee: and contrarily, we as well as they, by the collation of one Nation to another, haue our feete vpwards and our heads downeward. None can deny the Heauens to bee round, where then doth the Sun riſe when he ſets from vs? Some ſay it riſeth in the Antipodes; Why then if the Sunne bee with them all the while hee is abſent from vs, wee are the Antipodes. Againe, it is not to bee doubted that the Sea is round, yet when a ſhip hath ſayled ſo farre that the Pylot may iudge it to bee in the fartheſt and vttermoſt Region of the Watry-Wilderneſſe, yet the ſhip will not fall into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, which compaſſeth the Sea and Land round about, for they hang by the rare Art of the rareſt Geometrician, God: betweene the Heauens hauing all the Elements com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing them round about, ſo that which way ſoeuer wee goe, Heauen is ſtill aboue vs and beneath vs. Now if this be ſo, as it is not to bee doubted; why do not the Antipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that haue their feete oppoſite to ours, fall into the Heauens?</p>
               <p>No ſure, theſe Geographers were deceiued, for whereas they ſay the Antipodes were in a world vnder vs, they ſhould haue affirmed that they were,<note place="margin">Theſe are the true Antipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</note> and are, here with vs; and then I ſhould haue agreed with them, for there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that ſeldome or neuer ſee the Light, the Sunne riſe, or ſet:<note place="margin">Sence Epiſt. <hi>22.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> For what are Drunken-Alehouſes, Wine-tauernes, Bouſing-kens, and Victualing-houſes, where men drinke and ſwill, and neuer ſee any light, but that of a Candle to kindle their Tobacco, or that of the fire which burnes their Pipes, but the Antipodes? And doe not thoſe that in a peruerſe order, and quite retrograde from Nature, making the Day Night, and depriue themſelues not onely of the Common light, but the light of the Minde, by inuoluing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12869:21"/>themſelues in the thicke clouds of Ignorance and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, liue like true Antipodites? But for any other then theſe, I know not of, nor will acknowledge any other, whatſoeuer Aſtronomers or Geographers may affirme.</p>
               <p>But I feare I haue erred too farre out of the path I am bound to follow: therefore I will come into it againe.</p>
               <p>There cannot be a greater argument of the falſeneſſe of Aſtrologers, then the deadly Antypathie that is betweene them concerning the Art it ſelfe: for ſome of them hold, that the Degrees, Planets, Qualities, Apparances, Ends,<note place="margin">Diuerſitates qualitatum &amp; influentiarum Coeli ab effecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus cognoſcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</note> Exaltations, and Fallings, they attribute to the Planets, may be attayned vnto by the diligent obſeruation of the Effects of the Heauens, who by degrees may come to the knowledge of the Cauſes: for they thinke, that in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the World God gaue Men ſo long liues, that they might giue their Minds to Speculation, whereby they might finde out Aſtronomie, Aſtrologie, and ſuch Arts and Sciences, which require a long, large, and exact experience. In this I beleeue they ſay true: for ſome ſay, (it is a ſinne to belye the Deuill) by long obſeruation they may learne many experiments concerning Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie; yet, if by meere experience they had attayned to the Principles, then not once, but often, they ſhould haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the ſame Conſtellation, which is oppoſite to the Tenent of moſt of them, who hold, that the ſame Conſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation cannot appeare wholly againe, vnleſſe it be after the reuolution of many thouſand yeeres: and if they could perceiue them ſooner, yet doth it not ſuffice to obſerue the ſame particular Conſtellation, becauſe ſeeing the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of no Starre tends vpward, it is decreed by Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, that it is vncertaine whether the experimentall effect is to be aſcribed to this or that Planet, vnleſſe by chance it be to the Sunne or the Moone, which are often propoſed to vs in operation, when oftentimes they are the influence of a leſſer Starre, although farther from vs.<note place="margin">Nota.</note> For another
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12869:22"/>Conſtellation in ſuperior parts doth vary, hinder, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the operation of Heauen in inferior parts, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the matter.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe the influences of Conſtellations may be vnderſtood, yet they are not ſufficiently made manifeſt, as may appeare to him that reades the many doubts that ariſe about Aſtrologie, concerning the Motion of the Starres, the Firmament, and the Planets.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Stellarum fixa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum motus tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex.</note>Some graunt, that there is a Heauen aboue the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: ſome late Writers make vſe of and practiſe another Heauen; the <hi>Chaldaeans</hi> and <hi>Aegyptians</hi> one Motion, that is to ſay, diurnall to the Starres: <hi>Ptholomey</hi> addes a ſecond, which is from the Eaſt to the Weſt; <hi>Thebit</hi> a third, which is from the North to the South: but they all varie about the Time. And wonder not, if they vary about the fixt Starre, ſeeing they differ about the Motion of the Sunne and the Moone, for the preciſe knowledge of the Solar yeere: and it is needleſſe to report, how much they differ about the declination of the Sunne.</p>
               <p>Therefore, why ſhould any man beleeue them, when their Writings and Opinions differ ſo farre from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? for it is certaine, that if Aſtrologers be deceiued but in one Degree, in taking an Houre, they erre likewiſe in the diuiſion of the Houſes; for the Degree will change the Signe: then is it neceſſarie that their experiments are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers Prize.</note>The <hi>Chaldaeans</hi> (the moſt ancienteſt Aſtrologers) differ from the Opinion of the <hi>Aegyptians;</hi> for the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> diuide the Zodiake into twelue Signes, but the <hi>Chaldaeans</hi> into eleuen Images. Againe, ſome of them diſagree in their Degrees: ſome of them will haue this Planet placed in this Houſe, another in the third, fourth, fift, or ſixt. Thus is there ſuch a deadly enmitie betweene theſe Heauenly Doctors, that like ſo many Maſters of the Noble Science of Defence, they ſtriue to breake the head of each others reputation, and ſtand at defiance with each other. For
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:12869:22"/>when <hi>Ptholomie</hi> hath his <hi>Iacobs</hi> Staffe in his hand, hee thought himſelfe as skilfull at it as <hi>Turner</hi> was at his Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier and Dagger, and was aſſured, that <hi>Hermes Treſmegiſtus</hi> durſt not ſtand vp againſt him. When <hi>Alchibicius</hi> had got hold of his Aſtrolabe, hee was as ſafe as <hi>Robin</hi> the Deuill with his Sword and Targuet, and durſt prognoſticate, that neyther <hi>Albumazar</hi> nor <hi>Aboazar</hi> durſt challenge him. When <hi>Abraham Haly,</hi> or <hi>Thebit,</hi> were peeping through their Proſpectiue Glaſſes, they did beleeue, that neyther <hi>Auenozra</hi> nor <hi>Algazel</hi> durſt looke them in the face. Nay, doe but looke into the humours of our Moderne Calculators, and you ſhall finde them rayle one againſt another as bitterly as <hi>Naſh</hi> againſt <hi>Haruy;</hi> and why is all this? but becauſe they condemne each other for ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; when Heauen and Earth, God and Man, know, that he that lyeth the ſeldomeſt, doth lye very often.</p>
               <p>Some of them will prognoſticate, that on ſuch a day very vnfallibly there ſhall be Raine, when it is a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pound to a Farthing Token, but all the people dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in that Meridian his Almanacke was calculated for, but will finde them Lyars; except ſome Widdowes, that haue buryed their Husbands, or Sonnes their Fathers, who raine whole ſhowers of teares from their clouded eyes, it may be more for ioy then ſorrow. Another will fore-tell of Lightning and Thunder that ſhall happen ſuch a day, when there are no ſuch Inflamations ſeene, except men goe to the <hi>Fortune</hi> in <hi>Golding-Lane,</hi> to ſee the Tragedie of Doctor <hi>Fauſtus.</hi> There indeede a man may behold ſhagge-hayr'd Deuills runne roaring ouer the Stage with Squibs in their mouthes, while Drummers make Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the Tyring-houſe, and the twelue-penny Hirelings make artificiall Lightning in their Heauens. A third will fore-tell, that great Darkeneſſe ſhall happen on ſuch a day, when it may be none finde it true but Drunkards, that moſt commonly drinke themſelues ſo blinde, that they cannot ſee day-light.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:12869:23"/>
               <p>Who then will beleeue theſe Fortune-ſellers? for whom it is as eaſie at all times to tell true, as to make a thrice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carted <hi>Maquerella</hi> forſake her <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetian</hi> Tinctures, and paint her old wrinkled face with a modeſt bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh.</p>
               <p>Yet which is moſt ſtrange, and to be wondred at, I read one of their Predictions, which hitherto hath proued true; which was,<note place="margin">This is excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding true.</note> that from the yeere 1617. to the end of the World, ſhould be great Fires in many parts of the Citie of <hi>London:</hi> which hitherto hath proued true, to the no ſmall admiration of the Reader, and the no leſſe prayſe to the Calculator. For there haue beene ſuch hot fires in <hi>Pickt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hatch, Turne-bole ſtreet,</hi> the <hi>Myneryes,</hi> and both the <hi>Fryers,</hi> and other ſuch religious places, where <hi>Verus</hi> Nunnes are Cloyſtered, that if <hi>Tom Todd</hi> and his fellow fleſh-dreſſers had not quencht thoſe inflamations, many three-chin'd Bawd, dry-fiſted Punke, and bisket-handed Pandar would haue had all their hayre burnt off long ere this. There haue beene great fires many Moneths together in the <hi>Old-Bayly,</hi> ſo that many haue beene burnt in the Hand, and very glad they could ſcape ſo to. Many Drunkards haue had terrible heart-burnings with drinking ſtale Beere, and vehement hot inflamations at their ſtomacke with drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king hot Waters, ſo that many of them dare not goe to bed without a Thurrondell Pot of ſix ſhillings Beere ſtand by them all night, for feare their throats be ſet on fire before the next morning. Prodigalls haue had many phantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call fires in their braines, that haue almoſt burnt vp their Wit.</p>
               <p>But that which moſt grieues me, is, moſt of the Varlets belonging to the Citie Colledges (I meane both the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious Compters) haue fierie red faces,<note place="margin">Excellent pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to breed vp youth in.</note> that they cannot put a Cup of Nippitato to their Snowts, but with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme heat that doth glow from them, they make it cry hiſſe againe, as if there were a Gadd of burning Steele flung into the Pot. But becauſe I doe cruelly loue them, I will be their <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> and preſcribe this Medicine
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12869:23"/>following: Let them euery morning take a ſpoonefull of <hi>Aqua Fortis,</hi> rather <hi>Aqua Regis,</hi> as much <hi>Olcum Origanum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Probatum eſt</hi> for the cure of Red Noſes.</note> and mingle it with a little <hi>Mercurie</hi> ſublimate: then take a piece of the courſeſt haire-cloth, and dip it in this liquor, and ſo euery morning, while their Noſes is well, wet them with this Medicine, and it will doe all the Compter-Kites as much good as the World can deſire: for it ſtands to great reaſon it ſhould cure them, for one heat alwayes driues out another; why elſe doe Cookes that burne their fingers, hold them to the fire, but that the greater heat ſhould expell the leſſe? or why doe footmen, in the hoteſt Weather, after they haue runne a Race, drinke ſo much <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſquebah</hi> and <hi>Roſa Solis,</hi> but that it frights away the other? But I will leaue this Medicine to them, hoping they will take it, for it is for their good: and now I will come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to our Praedictions.</p>
               <p>There hath beene day and night continuall Fires in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet</hi> and the <hi>Strand,</hi> and in many other places of the Citie, but eſpecially in Tobacco ſhops, ſo that there cannot a man come in, but his Noſe will ſmoake for it.</p>
               <p>Thus once in their liues they haue told truth: yet this doth not giue ſatisfaction for the whole Legend of Lyes they yeerely ſet forth, and who ſo artificially tell them, that they well may be called Lyes in Print.</p>
               <p>Yet, howſoeuer they doe often miſſe in their Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, when they fore-tell of the diſpoſition of the Weather, of Warre, of Sickneſſe, of the Change of Times, and of Lawes; yet I cannot deny altogether, but that future Contingences may bee ſeene by the Contemplation of Heauen. For there is none can doubt, but that God, the great Architect of this viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and inuiſible World, infuſed a manyfold vertue and operation in the Heauens: but that many of theſe Qualities are ſecret, and occult, the Kingly Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> telleth vs, ſaying;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.6.</note> God numbreth the multitude of Starres, and impoſeth ſeuerall Names vnto them.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:12869:24"/>Therefore it is manifeſt, that things are named according to their properties, which none but hee that made them, can perfectly and diſtinctly vnderſtand.</p>
               <p>Yet many Philoſophers by their Speculation knew and obſerued the generall Influence of Heauen, by their Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Heat,<note place="margin">Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>r Me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rcr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp; de Generation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and Light: which made <hi>Ariſtoile</hi> affirme, That this Elementarie World is contiguous to Heauen, and that the Sunne, vnder the Oblique Circle, or the Zodiake, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Generations. Which is not abſurd to affirme: for certainely, the thicke and groſſe Bodyes are gouerned by the thinne,<note place="margin">Corpora inferiora ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ciuntur ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periorum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and that the influences of the Starres doe rule the differences of Bodyes; as in the Sunnes riſing or ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, we ſee the times of the yeere doe varie, and by the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and decreaſe of the Moone, ſome Creatures are aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, and diminiſhed: as ſhell-fiſh, at the wonderfull flux and reflux of the Sea. But to be of the Aſtrologers Opinion, that the Starres haue a power ouer the Will of Man, I neuer will beleeue; for the Mind cannot be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the Poſition of any Starre: Nor is it at all times true, that the differences of Bodyes are cauſed by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of Heauen:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> diuerſitas.</note> for two Twinnes of diuers Sexes may be conceiued in the ſame inſtant a Man and a Woman. And though many hold, that there may be a generall Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence into Bodyes, yet not into the faculties of the Soule or Mind;<note place="margin">Not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> for a corporall ſubſtance cannot cauſe an operation in a ſpirituall eſſence.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The true cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> why they ſtraggle from the Truck.</note>But the reaſon that many Aſtrologers and Prognoſtica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors erre in their Opinion (although there be an Influence in the Starres concerning the fertilitie of the Yeere, of Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence, of Warre, of Thunder, Haile, Raine, faire or foule Weather) is, becauſe they doe not keepe themſelues within the compaſſe of Aſtrologie, but thirſtie after Vaine-glory, goe beyond their limits, thinking to preſage that by Starres which poſſibly they cannot do. Againe, moſt Aſtrologers in former Ages held diuers opinions concerning the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Aſtrologie, and they (though but Pupils in this
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12869:24"/>Art) preſume to come in with their Opinions, becauſe they would be thought Maſters of their Art: and although of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes they hit vpon the diſpoſition of the Weather, and future things, by the obſeruation of the Heauens; yet at all times, concerning the diſpoſition of Corne eſpecially, they cannot chuſe but erre, becauſe the foure parts of the yeere are ſo different in Qualitie, ſo that it is impoſſible, but that the exceſſe of Heat in one part of the yeere, and the exceſſe of cold in the other doth diſtemper the Soyle. Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Praedictions of Diſeaſes, they may the eaſieſt tell, for by the corruption of the Ayre, Phyſicke teacheth vs, many infections may putrifie the braine.</p>
               <p>This onely ſhall ſuffice for Aſtrologers. Now I will come to the Art it ſelfe; whereby they can calculate Deaths and Natiuities, tell Fortunes either good or bad: which they fetch as farre as from the Twelue Houſes they haue built in Heauen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſignification of the Twelue Houſes <hi>of Heauen.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THeſe Twelue Houſes are the Tenements moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſuch Aſtrologers as you your ſelfe doe let out to ſimple people, whereby they purchaſe to themſelues much Money, and to their Tenants much ſorrow. And to tell truth, theſe Twelue Signes, placed in their Twelue Houſes, are like a Iury that ſit vpon the life and death of Mortalitie.</p>
               <p>By the diſpoſition of the firſt Houſe,<note place="margin">The 1. Houſe.</note> by the Planets and Starres fixt in it, by the natures and diuers effects that are wrought by them, many Wonders are diſcouered: as to know of what condition he ſhall be of, either as liberall as an Aldermans Sonne and Heire, or as penurious as the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Catch-pole, that will feed his Dogges with Rabbers in Lent, while he ſits eating a piece of poore <hi>Iohn:</hi> it can tell
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12869:25"/>of what vocation or calling a Man ſhall bee of, either a Stubble-bearded-Bariſter, and wrangle ſtoutly and loudly at the Barre, or whether hee ſhall bee a Souldier, and fight brauely, if a man doe but ſcorne for to pledge him a deepe health vnto ſome of his White-Fryer Miſtreſſes, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>By the ſecond Houſe you can foretell of the proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or aduerſitie of him that is borne:<note place="margin">The 2. Houſe.</note> whether hee ſhall be a rich Citizen, and breake three or foure ſeuerall times of ſet purpoſe, either of ſet purpoſe to couſen the world, or out of meere pouertie; whether he ſhall be an Heire, and inherit his Fathers vices as well as his riches, or whether he ſhall be a Marchant and looſe his goods on ſalt Seas, or haue them drown'd in the <hi>Canaries</hi> of ſome Tauerne.</p>
               <p>By the third Houſe you can iudge of the ſecreſie of the Conſcience,<note place="margin">The 3. Houſe.</note> whether it be good or bad toward God, or Man. In my Conſcience they erre from the truth at the leaſt a thouſand <hi>Dutch</hi> miles, becauſe the Holy Ghoſt tells vs, that no man knowes whether he deſerues Hate or Loue; ſo that by this we may perceiue that the ſecrets of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience are onely knowne to God.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſia.</hi> 9.</note> Therefore this madnes of the Aſtrologers is not only to be confuted, but burnt for an hereſie. Beſides this wickednes, they hold there are two moſt fortunate Planets aboue all the reſt; which are, <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Iupiter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Planets</note> and that <hi>Venus</hi> giues the felicitie of this life, and <hi>Iupiter</hi> of the life to come, which I vtterly diſallow of: for if a man follow ſuch a wanton wench as <hi>Venus</hi> is, he ſhall in ſmall time lye ſweating in ſome hoſpitall, or groning in ſome Barber Chirurgions houſe, which I thinke can be no great felicity; and he that follows the humor of Iouiall <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> ſhall find, and quickly know, that he deſerues that place which is contrary to immortality. So that by the aſſertion of theſe Aſtrologers, whoſoeuer is borne when <hi>Venus</hi> raigns ſhall liue in this world moſt pleaſantly, in ſpight of ill For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune and when <hi>Iupiter</hi> raignes, he ſhall liue in the world to come, although he liue neuer ſo wickedly, for you make no
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12869:25"/>exception, but indefinitely ſay, They ſhall.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Maternus Aſtrolog.</note> 
                  <hi>Maternus</hi> was as mad, or rather as wicked as the reſt, who writes and affirmes, that when <hi>Saturne</hi> is placed in <hi>Leo,</hi> men liue long, whoſe ſoules afterward ſhall go to God. Marke but how confidently and arrogantly hee ſpeakes this, which I will confute with the words of our Sauiour, who ſaith:<note place="margin">Math. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Whoſoeuer will enter into the Kingdome of God, muſt keepe his Commandements.</hi> And not whoſoeuer will enter into the kingdome of God muſt be borne when <hi>Saturne</hi> is in <hi>Leo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Albumazar</hi> alſo is as diuelliſh as the reſt,<note place="margin">Albumazar</note> heaping impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie on impietie; affirming that he that prayes to God in the houre in which the Moone with the head of the Dragon is ioyned to <hi>Iupiter,</hi> ſhall obtaine whatſoeuer hee asketh. If this ſacrilegious foolery is true, why do not the Aſtrologers themſelues obſerue this houre, that they may pray that they may neuer more erre, or that they may obtaine ſo much riches that they neuer after may be forced to ſet their lyes to ſale, or that they may liue no more on the foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penny reward of ſome Suburbe-ſinner, for caſting her hot water; or the ſix-penny gratuitie of ſome old Maide ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant that would be loath to die a Virgin: or they may pray that they neuer more ſell their good Fortunes to Oyſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiues and Butte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-women for greaſie Two-pences? But by this Argument that you cannot follow that you preſcribe to others, a man may ſmell your Roguery to be as ranke as a Mountaine-Goate.</p>
               <p>By the fourth Houſe,<note place="margin">The 4. Houſe.</note> you will iudge of the eſſence of the Child that is borne, how long it ſhall liue, and how well: if it ſhall be as long liued as a Rauen, or Stagge; or as ſhortliued as a Goate, or Cocke-Sparrow.</p>
               <p>By the fifth Houſe you can iudge, how hee ſhall liue, and affect his Parents,<note place="margin">The 5. Houſe.</note> whether he ſhall loue his Father better then his Mother, or his Mother then his Father. <hi>Ptolomey</hi> thinkes you may iudge by the tenth Houſe, but <hi>Mallius ab Aſcendente.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:12869:26"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 6. Houſe.</note>By the ſixth Houſe you will know of what Profeſſion it ſhall be of, either a Foole, or a Phyſition; a Paraſite, or a Courtier; a Begger, or an Alchymiſt; a mad Man, or a Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; a Thiefe, or a Taylor.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 7. Houſe.</note>By the ſeuenth Houſe you will iudge what wife he ſhall haue, either a delicate yong plumpe <hi>Helena,</hi> that lookes as merry as may, and as iocound as Iune; or an old decrepite <hi>Lamia,</hi> that is as froſty as February, and as dull as Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; whether ſhe ſhall be as mute as a Fiſh, or haue a tongue as loude as a Fiſh-Wife.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 8. Houſe.</note>By the eight Houſe you will iudge how vnfortunately a man will die, either on the water, like a Pyrate, or in the water like a Fiſh, or on a tree like a High-way man, or on the bow like a Bird: whether hee ſhall be ſtaru'd to death in a Priſon, like ſome Prodigall; or in ſome Burdello, like a French Monſier, or a Spaniſh Don, whoſe bones the Neopolitan Dogge hath pickt ſo cleane, that they would ſerue well ſome Gilder to Burniſh with.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 9 Houſe.</note>By the ninth Houſe you can iudge, whether he ſhall be a Traueller, as famous as our Engliſh <hi>Coriate,</hi> or outlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh <hi>Peter Columbus;</hi> what fortune he ſhall haue in his tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, what faſhions he ſhall weare.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 10. houſe</note>By the tenth Houſe you can iudge of the ſtate of the Mother.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 11. houſe.</note>By the eleuenth Houſe, you can iudge of what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion he ſhall be, Sanguine, Chollericke, Phlegmaticke, or Melancholy, or what haire he ſhall be of, of a Browne or <hi>Abraham</hi> colour, as the Engliſh; of a Yellow, as the Dane; Flaxen, as the Iriſh; or Blacke, as the Spaniard.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 12. houſe</note>The twelfth and laſt Houſe, where he ſhall dwell, and what neighbours he ſhall haue.</p>
               <p>Thus haue I runne ouer the twelue Celeſtiall Houſes, whereby you can infallibly foretell of our good or bad for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, according to the Nature and Influence of that Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net that raigned at our births, in which you are moſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentably deceiued: for you ſay, there is no man borne but
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12869:26"/>he is borne either vnder an Auſpitious, or Maleuolent Star, and according to that Planets influence he is borne vnder, he ſhall thriue and proſper; alſo you ſay, that euery Planet hath but one influence, either good or bad, now that this is falſe I inſtantly will proue.</p>
               <p>I haue heard of two brethren that were Twins, now there is no Aſtrologer will deny,<note place="margin">Gemini.</note> but that theſe brethren were borne vnder one Conſtellation, becauſe they were borne within the ſpace of one Minute, and being borne vnder a Maleuolent Sarre they muſt bee both vnfortunate, and vnder a ſmiling and luckie Starre, happy. But not long after the birth of theſe Twins there was a Fortune-teller did calculate their natiuities,<note place="margin">No Planet hath a double influence.</note> and told the Parents of theſe chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren that they ſhould both be fortunate, becauſe he percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued they were borne vnder a fortunate Planet, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued contrary to his predictions: For theſe wanting meanes belike to ſupply their wants, being come to mens eſtates, did againſt ſome good Time (although they had no Lands or Tenements of their owne) take vp other mens rents ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on New-market heath, or Salisbury plaine: who for thoſe facts, to be ſhort, were taken, carryed before a Iuſtice, by him committed to Priſon, the next Sizes were brought to their triall, conuicted, condemned, and iudged to bee hanged. Now all this while their Fortunes were equall, but contrary to the Prediction of the Aſtrologer; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the Starre that raigned at their births had a double in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, which is contrary to your writings, for when theſe brethren were brought to the place of execution, and ready to be turned off, there came a repriue for the yongeſt, who was carryed backe againe to priſon, had his pardon, and afterward became an honeſt man; but the eldeſt with the loſſe of his life ſatisfied the Law.</p>
               <p>There was another Aſtrologer did diuine, that one <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nello Foroboſco</hi> a notorious thiefe ſhould be hanged,<note place="margin">Donello Foro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſco.</note> which did come ſomething nigh his Prediction, for he beeing a hungry <hi>Lazarallo de Tormes,</hi> robd Market women, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12869:27"/>country people of Cheeſe-Cakes, and Butter milke, for which fact hee was apprehended and condemned to bee hanged: ſo comming to the gallowes, hee ſtudied how hee might eſcape that deſtinie; at the laſt, ſeeing his time, hee flung Ginny-Pepper in the Hangmans eyes as he came to put the nooze ouer his necke,<note place="margin">Scorning han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with his heeles.</note> lept off the ladder, and ſhewed himſelfe a very nimble footman, for he ran away, making toward the Sea, which was nigh the place of execution, and endeuouring to ſwim to ſaue himſelfe from thoſe that purſued him, the Crampe tooke him in the great Toe; and ſo, whereas by the law of Nations, and the opinion of the Aſtrologer hee ſhould haue beene hanged, hee was moſt vnfortunately drowned: and thus theſe learned Aſtrologers were deceiued.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Eraſmus in lingualatina.</note>It ſtands to great reaſon, that theſe Artiſts cannot at all times tell others mens fortunes, when they cannot fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell of their owne good or bad lucke: For there was an Aſtrologer made a prediction of <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſeuenths death, (but ſome attribute this to <hi>Alphonſus</hi> king of <hi>Arragon</hi>) and that hee ſhould die on ſuch a yeare. The King hearing of this South-ſayer, ſent for him, and askt him if he were an Aſtrologer, and could tell Fortunes, to whom he anſwered yes; The King againe askt him if hee neuer did foreſee by his Art that there was imminent danger, that much about that time ſhould hang ouer his head, meaning the Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, to whom he anſwerd no: Then the King replyed, thou art a fooliſh Eigure-Caſter, for I am more skilfull then thou art; for as ſoone as I ſaw thee, I inſtantly propheſied thou ſhouldſt be in priſon before night, which thou ſhalt finde true: ſo the King inſtantly ſent him thither. But hee had not beene long in cuſtody, but the King ſent for him again to know if he could caſt a Figure truely, to know how long he ſhould be in priſon: to whom he ſtill anſwered no; then the King ſayd, thou art an illiterate fellow, that neither can foretell of either good or badde lucke that ſhall befall thy ſelfe; therefore I will conclude, thou canſt not foretell of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12869:27"/>mine: ſo forthwith ſet him at libertie, giuing him many diſgracefull words.</p>
               <p>Yet howſoeuer theſe examples touch the reputation of thoſe that profeſſe your Art; yet I will not infallibly ſay, that ſuch things were neuer done, although it be not ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie to doe them: for it is almoſt incredible to beleeue, yet I perſwade my ſelfe that it is true what <hi>Zonaras</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, That the day before <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata dyed,<note place="margin">Zonaras.</note> a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine man lying in a ſolitarie place by himſelfe, ſaw a heape of Starres in the Element, which he ſaid did expreſſe theſe words, <hi>Hodie</hi> Iulianus <hi>in</hi> Perſia <hi>occiditur;</hi> That this day <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtata is ſlaine in <hi>Perſia:</hi> and the time being afterwards noted, it was perfectly knowne that hee dyed that day. But this I take to be an extraordinarie reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Another Aſtrologer did fore-tell a Prelate, an acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of his, that hee ſhould haue a great fall: Therefore the Prelate, that he might be the more ſafe (knowing the Aſtrologer to be a learned Man) would neuer goe higher then the loweſt Roome of his Houſe; would neuer dyne, or ſuppe, but ſit on the ground; when hee went to bed, would lye on the ground; hoping by this warineſſe, to change the Poſition of the Starre that did threaten him: but it was in vaine; for a while after newes was brought him, that he was depoſed of his Biſhoprick: who inſtantly cryed out, Now the Aſtrologers Prediction is come to paſſe, for indeed I can fall no lower.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Byron,</hi> Marſhall of <hi>France,</hi> was told by a Wizard,<note place="margin">Byron.</note> that a <hi>Burgundian</hi> ſhould be the death of him: vpon which Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction he gaue expreſſe command, That not a man of that Nation ſhould come nigh him: but all would not helpe, for hee found the Prediction true, by the loſſe of his Head, which a <hi>Burgundian</hi> cut off, that was his Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner. Theſe two laſt ſeeme to ſauour ſomewhat of the Deuills Subtilties, and the Aſtrologers Amphibolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:12869:28"/>
               <p>There was another Wizard (as it was reported to me by a learned and rare Scholler, as we were diſcourſing about Aſtrologie) that ſome twentie yeeres before his death told <hi>Cuffe</hi> our Countreyman, and a moſt excellent <hi>Graecian,</hi> that hee ſhould come to an vntimely end: at which, <hi>Cuffe</hi> laughed, and in a ſcoffing manner entreated the Aſtrologer to ſhew him in what manner he ſhould come to his end: who condiſcended to him, and calling for Cards, entreated <hi>Cuffe</hi> to draw out of the Packe three, which pleaſed him; who did ſo, and drew three Knaues: who (by the Wizards direction) layd them on the Table againe with their faces downewards, and then told him, if hee deſired to ſee the ſumme of his bad fortunes reckoned vp, to take vp thoſe Cards one after the other, and looke on the inſide of them, and he ſhould be truly reſolued of his future fortunes. <hi>Cuffe</hi> did as he was preſcribed, and firſt took vp the firſt Card, and looking on it, he ſaw the true portraiture of himſelfe <hi>Cape a Pe,</hi> hauing men compaſſing him about with Bills and Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berds: then he tooke vp the ſecond Card, and there ſaw the Iudge that ſat vpon him: at laſt, he tooke vp the laſt Card, &amp; ſaw <hi>Tyborne,</hi> the place of his Execution, &amp; the Hangman, at which he then laughed heartily; but many yeres after, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condemned for Treaſon, he remembred the fatall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the Wizard, &amp; before his death reuealed it to ſome of his friends. If this be true, it was more then Aſtrology, and no better then flat Sorcery or Coniuring, which is diuelliſh.</p>
               <p>There was another (with whom I will end) that was told by a Scholler,<note place="margin">An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>us.</note> that he ſhould haue his braines beaten out: but he was ſo warie of himſelfe, that he would not lye in a houſe for feare the roofe ſhould fall on his head, reſoluing to lye in a Tent; but that reſolution laſted not long, for he durſt not truſt himſelfe there, for feare the great Pole, that went croſſe ouer it, ſhould knock him on the head: then he reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to lye vnder ſome Tree, but then he feared, if he ſhould fall aſleepe in a windy night, the Tree might fall on him. He durſt not goe into any Towne, leſt a Tyle ſhould crack his
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:12869:28"/>crowne: ſo that what place ſoeuer he went into, he ſtill was very wary of himſelfe. At the laſt, as he was walking in a hot Summers day in the fields, he was forced to put off his Hat, and hauing a bald Head, a ſtrange Bird that was in the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hauing an Oyſter in her claw, thinking it to be ſome white ſtone, let it fall on his head, &amp; ſo beat out his braines. Thus for all his care &amp; prouidence, he came to his vntimely end, and fulfilled the Prediction of the Aſtrologer, or rather Coniurer, if the Tale be true, which I ſcarce beleeue.</p>
               <p>Thus Sir you ſee I will not ſo much diſparage your black Art, as to ſay, that you cannot fore tell of things to come, calculate Natiuities, or do ſtrange things, though not by it, but by the helpe of the Deuill, who abuſeth you: but I ſay they ought not to be done, becauſe as S. <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Ierom. in Com. ſuper Prophetam Sophoniam.</note> you lift vp your ſelfe againſt the knowledge of God, giuing your ſelues to a fained Art, imputing euery accident that happens in a yeere, or an age, to the riſing or ſetting of Starres,<note place="margin">Gregan Homeli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Epiphaniae ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta occaſione ab apparitione Stella quam Magi viderunt in Oriente Nato Domino contra Mathematicos orationem tex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens. Ambroſ. in <hi>4.</hi> lib. Hexa. Auguſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne.</note> thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that humane affaires are managed by the courſe &amp; fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Starres, and while you promiſe health to others, you are ignorant of your own puniſhments. Again he ſaith, That to ſeeke out the courſe of the Starres, &amp; the euents that follow them, is the ſcandal of <hi>Egypt,</hi> &amp; plain Idolatry. S. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> ſaith, He that thinks to expreſſe the ſeuerall qualities of Natiuities, &amp; will tell what diſpoſition the child ſhalbe of as ſoone as it is borne, is both a villanous &amp; vaine man, becauſe it is moſt wicked &amp; impoſſible to do. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, That theſe Aſtrologers &amp; Southſayers hold, that all things good or bad happen by Fortune, which is moſt wicked &amp; Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh: for the <hi>Gentils</hi> called <hi>Fortuna, Dea,</hi> or a Diuine Power, not conſidering any mans merits, but gaue riches to one and miſery to another. And the better to expreſſe her, they made her Image according to the forme of a Woman, ſitting in the middle of a Wheele, alwayes turning it, hauing the right ſide of her face bright, the left obſcure, yet both blind; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that thoſe ſhe fauoured, were merry and iocund, but thoſe ſhe hated, diſcontent and melancholy. Her blindneſſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12869:29"/>ſhewed the indifference both of the good and bad: by the Wheele, they did ſhew the prodigious change of this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant Goddeſſe; which is impious, and againſt all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith: for wee ought to conſider, that all the ill that happens to vs, haue their originall from our ſinnes, and all the benefits and good that comes to vs, from the mercies of God, and not from this or that maleuolent or ſmiling Star, or from the frown or ſmile of Fortune.</p>
               <p>But if you will haue theſe accidents good, or bad, that happen in a minute of an houre, and ſometimes in larger and leſſer diſtances of time to Fortune, ſhee is very predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minant among vs, and like one of the moſt powerfulleſt Planets raignes and rules ouer our Natiuities and Affaires. For it is ſome mens fortune to be Citizens, ſome againe to be Cuckolds; ſome mens fortune to be Courtiers, ſome to be Flatterers; ſome to be Schollers, ſome to be Fooles; ſome to be Lawyers, ſome to be Knaues; ſome to be Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, ſome to be Deuils; ſome to be Captaines, ſome to be Cowards; ſome to be Beggars, ſome to be Alchymiſts; ſome to be Heires, ſome to be Fooles; ſome to be younger Brothers, &amp; ſome to be Wiſe-men. Again, it hath bin many a Gallants good fortune to haue a braue Sute of Clothes on his back on the morning,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nfortunium.</note> yet it hath bin his bad fortune to haue them in the Lumbard before night:<note place="margin">Diſſortunium.</note> it hath beene many honeſt mens good fortune to haue a faire Wife, yet it hath beene his bad fortune, not to know truly how many Children he hath had by her of his owne getting. It hath beene many a roating Boyes good fortune (as they ſay) to kill his enemie in the field, yet it hath beene his bad fortune to be hanged for it the next Seſſions.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee your Goddeſſe <hi>Fortune</hi> hath a great predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minance ouer this lower World the earth: yet howſoeuer, I will not beleeue theſe things happen by fortune, and the meere influence of the Starres; therefore let all men auoid them, for this opinion cauſeth many to affirme there is no God.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:12869:29"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aſtrology no Art but a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</hi> Aug. Contra Mathematicos in Capitulo quanto &amp; in fine Capit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> will not allow of your Aſtrologie, but calleth it a meere vanitie; and thoſe that profeſſe it, ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Truth: he ſaith, that the diuell firſt found out this Art, and thoſe that are curious in it are enemies to God, becauſe it breeds many ſuperſtitious opinions in men and women, eſpecially the ancienteſt, which they hold as cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall, and as lawfull to bee obſerued and followed as any part of the Scripture, of which I will reckon vp ſome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A CATALOGVE OF MANY SV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Ceremonies, eſpecially old men and women hold, which were firſt found out and inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Figure-Caſters, Cunning Men and Women in former ages, yet to this day are held for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and true obſeruations.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1 <hi>THat if any thing be loſt amongſt a company of ſeruants, with the tricke of the Siue and the Sheeres, it may be found out againe, and who ſtole it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>That Toothaches, Agues, Cramps, and Feuers, and many other diſeaſes may bee healed by mumbling a few strange words ouer the head of the diſeaſed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>That by a certaine tuft of haire growing on the foremoſt part of a mans forehead, it may be knowne whether he ſhall bee a widdower or no.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>That a man may know whats a clocke, onely by a Ring and a ſiluer Beaker.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 <hi>That it is very ill lucke to haue a Hare croſſe one in the high way.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6 <hi>That to haue yellow ſpeckles on the nailes of ones hand is a great ſigne of death.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7 <hi>That when the left cheeke burnes, it is a ſigne ſome bodie talkes well of you, but if the right cheeke burnes it is a ſigne of ill.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:12869:30"/>
                  <item>8 <hi>That when a mans noſe bleeds but a drop or two, that it is a ſigne of ill lucke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>9 <hi>That when a mans noſe bleeds but one drop, and at the left noſtril, it is a ſigne of good lucke, but on the right ill.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>10 <hi>That if a man ſtumbles in a morning as ſoone as he comes out of dores, it is a ſigne of ill lucke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>11 <hi>That if a man walking in the fields, finde any foure-leaued graſſe, he ſhall in a ſmall while after finde ſome good thing.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>12 <hi>That it is not good to put on a new ſute, pare ones nailes, or begin any thing on a Childermas day.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>13 <hi>That if a man be drowſie, it is a ſigne of ill lucke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>14 <hi>That it is a ſigne of ill lucke to finde money.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>15 <hi>That it is naught for a man or women to loſe their hoſe Garter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>16 <hi>That it is a very vnfortunate thing for a man to meete early in a morning an ilfauoured man or woman, a rough-footed Hen, a ſhag-haird Dogge, or a blacke Cat.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>17 <hi>That it is a ſigne of death to ſome in that houſe, where Cric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets haue bin many yeeres, if on a ſudden they forſake the Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Corner.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>18 <hi>That if a man dream of egs or fire, he ſhall heare of anger.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>19 <hi>That to dreame of the deuill is good lucke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>20 <hi>That to dreame of gold good lucke, but of ſiluer ill.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>21 <hi>That if a man be born in the day time, he ſhal be vnfortunate</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>22 <hi>That if a child be borne with a Caule on his head, he ſhall be very fortunate.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>23 <hi>That when the palme of the right hand itcheth, it is a ſhrewd ſigne he ſhall receiue money.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>24 <hi>That it is a great ſigne of ill lucke, if Rats gnaw a mans cloathes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>25 <hi>That it is naught for any man to giue a paire of kniues to his ſweet heart, for feare it cuts away all loue that is betweene them.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>26 <hi>That it is ill lucke to haue the Salt ſeller fall towards you.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>27 <hi>That if the Beere fall next a man, it is a ſigne of good luck.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>28 <hi>That if a Candle burne blew, it is a ſigne there is a ſpirit in the houſe, or not farre from it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:12869:30"/>
                  <item>29 <hi>That when the Cat waſheth her face ouer her eare, wee ſhall haue great ſtore of raine.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>30 <hi>That if a horſe ſtumble on the high way, it is a ſigne of ill lucke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>31 <hi>That when a mans noſe itcheth, it is a ſigne he ſhall drinke wine.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>32 <hi>That if your lips itch, you ſhall kiſſe ſome body.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>33 <hi>That it is a very ill ſigne to be Melancholy.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Theſe, and a thouſand more as vaine as theſe, I could reckon vp, were it not that I ſhould make too long a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion from my matter; with which ſo many people are ſo deepely beſotted, that a whole Vniuerſitie of Doctors cannot roote theſe ſuperſtitious obſeruations out of their minde: for what an idlenes is it in them, to thinke that there is either any <hi>Bonum</hi> or <hi>Malum omen</hi> in theſe things?<note place="margin">Bonum &amp; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Omen.</note> what ill lucke can there be in it, when a Hare eroſſeth you, except it is your ill lucke not to catch her, or when you haue caught her, to let her go againe? (as the Welchman did,) what ill lucke can it be to a man to ſtumble in a morning, except he fall down &amp; breake his noſe? what ill lucke can there be in finding mony, except it be counterfet? but if it be currant I cannot be perſwaded if he that takes it vp be not as as very a foole as <hi>Iohn</hi> of the Hoſpitall (that could not abide money) will take it for ill lucke, but if it be ill lucke, God ſend me that ill lucke euery day. What ill lucke is there in loſing a Hoſe garter, except it be to put a man to the charge to buy a new payre? So that I cannot picke out any thing in theſe obſeruations why they ſhould bee ſignes of good or badde lucke. Therefore I cannot perſwade my ſelfe, but you and ſuch Figure-flingers as you, that ſowe the ſuperſtitious ſeeds in the hearts of credulous people, is onely to get to your ſelues praiſe, but eſpeciall money. And you haue not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcattered theſe in or about the Citie, but in the Country: for many Townes haue beene peſtered with theſe Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, before the Lawes prepared whipping Poſts, Stocks, and Houſes of Correction for them, for theſe Rogues
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12869:31"/>before this preparation for them, would appeare in the vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages in the likeneſſe of <hi>Gypſies,</hi> which word indeed is deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> but by corruption of the tongue are called <hi>Gypſies:</hi> and that they might be thought to come of the iſſue of that Sun-burnt Generation, they with Herbs and Plants for the purpoſe would venome their skins, and with Oakers diſcolour their faces; and then for Bread, Beere, and Bacon, Cheeſe, eſpecially for money, would vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to tell poore Maide-ſeruants their Fortunes, which ſhould be ſure to be good, becauſe they would be ſure of good reward, and theſe poore ſilly creatures ſeeing them to be blacke and ill fauoured people, and it may be hearing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of ſome as wiſe as themſelues, of the <hi>Gypſies</hi> cunning, would eaſily beleeue that they were Cunning men, and doe ſtrange things. And it is a great Folly and Madneſſe of many, who neuer ſee a tawny viſaged man, with a blacke curled head of haire (eſpecially, if he be ſcholler, or profeſſe himſelfe to be one) but they will thinke he is a Cunning man and a Coniurer.</p>
               <p>But if they alwayes hold this to be true, they may as well ſay, that none dwell at the Kings head but Princes, nor at Queenes head but Ladies, none at the Popes head but Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, none at the Biſhops head but Diuines, none at the Maidenhead but Virgins, none at the Bull head but Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, none at the Rams head but Butchers, none at the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>razens head but Heathens, and none at the Nagges head but Horſcourſers; all which is moſt abſurd to beleeue: for if all thoſe that haue blacke heads or faces were Coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, then all Chimney Sweepers were Negromancers. Therefore I pittie the blinde ignorance of many Country people, and warne them to take heede of theſe Rogues that couſen whole townes as they come through,<note place="margin">This was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to me by the mouth of <hi>Bell</hi> himſelfe, Iaylor of Ipſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch.</note> as by this true diſcourſe following ſhall appeare.</p>
               <p>Not many yeares ſince there came a Crew of theſe Hedgecreepers trooping through <hi>Eſſex,</hi> telling Fortunes as they went: but at the laſt, the Conſtable by the vertue of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12869:31"/>his Office, &amp; the Statute againſt theſe Rogues, apprehended them, and brought them before a Iuſtice, who committed them to <hi>Ipſwitch</hi> Iayle, there to continue while next Sizes. In the meane time, one <hi>William Bell</hi> (that in my minde had bin fit to haue bin hanged vp for his Roguery) being then Iaylor, knowing the ſimplicitie of many of the Townes-mens wiues, daughters, and ſeruants, and the ſubtiltie of thoſe Rogues vnder his Cuſtody, came to them, telling them, that if they would bee as priuate as hee would be conſtant, he would lay a plot how they and himſelfe would get the beſt part of twenty Marke, cleere in their purſes,<note place="margin">A Comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> betweene a knaue &amp; a com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany of rogues</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Sizes; beſides, a purchaſing of their libertie. Theſe Trauellers at the firſt doubted, but at condeſcend to him, telling he ſhould haue a full halfe ſhare of whatſoeuer they got by acting that Comedy. <hi>Bell</hi> vpon this drew a large note of the names of the chiefeſt men and women in the Towne, their Complexions, Statures, the Colour and Faſhion of their Cloathes they ware, in what Streete they dwelt, at what Signe, what Suiters they had before they were marryed, of what eſtate he was that marryed any wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, whether he were a Widdower or a Batchler, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny children he hath had by her, how many Girles, how many Boyes, if they had any children before they were marryed; and whatſoeuer worthy of note, (many yeere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had hapned) he ſet downe in that Bill which he gaue to the <hi>Queeue of Fairies,</hi> I meane, the ancienteſt of thoſe ſhee Cunny-catchers to reade ouer, and diligently to peruſe, charging them neuer to anſwer to any thing that was askt them vpon the ſudden, but to withdraw themſelues into a roome, through which <hi>Bell</hi> had made hole with an Auger, that they might looke out and view thoſe that were in the next roome, that came to know their Fortunes; and when they had taken full notice of them, and what had happened them by the notice of the Bill, then to come openly to them, and tell them firſt what had befallen them, which was true; and what ſhould happen to them, which was moſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12869:32"/>falſe. Now this Iaylor, this Setter, this Cunny-catcher <hi>Bell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe forward ſchollers had learnt this leſſon perfectly went down into the town, as his order was euery afternoon to ſome Ale-houſe or other, but now did eſpecially chuſe one, where a very beleeuing olde woman dwelt, that had giuen many a Dubble iug of Beere and Ale to ſuch Rogues that had ſtopt her mouth full of lyes: and long after hee had entred into this drinking Schoole, and after a little diſcourſe with a company of countrey Corridons that ſate there tipling, he told them, that hee had a company of the ſtrangeſt men and women in his priſon that he euer heard of, for without any asking they had told him of many things that happened many yeeres before hee kept a priſon, and ſince hee kept a priſon, how many priſoners hee loſt, what men they were, what time of the yeere they brake out, on what day, and when hee found them againe. This begat no ſmall credite in them that heard him, but eſpecially in the olde woman, who as the nature of anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent people is, could not keepe newes long, told it to two or three of her neighbours, they to fortie more, ſo that <hi>Bells</hi> report in few howres flew vppe and downe the Towne, and tooke ſuch deepe roote in the mindes of moſt of the people, thae many of them could not bee at reſt while they had ſeene them, and then vnder the colour of ſeeing them, to know their Fortunes. Many repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thither, asking many queſtions of theſe wiſe Knaues, and Whores, who at the firſt would not bee drawne to tell them any thing; ſo withdrawing themſelues into their priuate Chamber, where they through the hole made for them a purpoſe, might take particular notice of all of them and when according to the direction of their Bill, did know euerie man and womans name there, and what had happened to them, at the laſt, they would come ſtealing out againe, and call euery man and woman by their names, tell them where they dwelt, and at what Signe, and whiſper the women in their eares,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12869:32"/>and make many of them bluſh, and for the men make them to laugh; ſo that theſe countrey people hearing themſelues named of them that neuer ſaw them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and told them of things that had beene done many yeeres before, wondred at them, and gaue them money, ſent them meate euery day to dinner and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, ſaying, it was pittie ſuch skilfull people as they ſhould not bee prouided for, ſo that for the ſpace of fiue weekes they were viſited more then all the Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nycatching Knaues about London: for there was not a Mayde that had gotten a clappe before ſhee was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed, a young Strippling that had got a Wench with childe, or any Farmer, or Townſman that had loſt his Purſe, or Horſe, or Sheepe many yeeres before, but would repayre to thoſe <hi>Gypſies,</hi> ſo that ſome gaue them wrought Handkerchers, Gloues, Purſes and Kniues, Money, and more Meate and Drinke, then twentie more of them could eate, and when the Sizes came, by meanes they made to the Iuſtices, procured their libertie, yet thought themſelues much beholding to them, not dreaming that any of theſe things were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed to them by <hi>Bell,</hi> who for his ſhare in the ſpace of three weekes, had got twenty marke cleare to himſelfe, which his knauery and the <hi>Gypſies</hi> roguery pickt out of the Townſmens pockets.</p>
               <p>The like roguery doth one (that goeth vnder the name of a Captaine vſe, who with the trickes and ſleights of legerdemaine, he doth on the Cards foole many people out of their money, making them beleeue hee can finde things out by Art, that when his owne conſcience knowes is farre from the knowledge or grounds of Aſtrologie, as hee from honeſtie, and if I were to talke or diſpute with him, I would confute him in the ſtrongeſt arguments he could produce to proue his skill, and to his face boldly iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie that he is but a meere Impoſtor, and can doe nothing
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12869:33"/>without the ayde and help of ſuch a knaue as himſelfe, who haue found out many things betwin them before they haue beene loſt; who firſt lay plots to haue things conueyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, then take money to finde them againe. If you, nor the world will beleeue this, let them but looke into Newgate books &amp; they ſhal find he ſtood in the Pillory for ſuch Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueries, hauing this faire inſcription written ouer his head in Capitall Letters, FOR COVSENAGE. But I will come backe againe to the matter I treated of before, which was of your cunning Aſtrologers, that can do theſe pretty trickes and ſleights by Art.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſtu libro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> de do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> calleth your Art a Sacraligious foolery, an vnlearned learning, and a kinde of fornication with the Soule.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> makes mention that Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, finding a Prieſt that found out a Thief that had robd the Church, by the inſpection into his Aſtralobe, ſuſpended him from his order for that fact for a yeere together, ſaying, it was a moſt haynous ſinne for a man of his order, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe ſuch an vnlawfull ſtudy, although it were for the good of the Church.</p>
               <p>Thus Sir, you ſee your Art is forbidden concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning telling of Fortunes, or finding out things that are loſt, &amp;c. And in forbidding the practiſe of this Art, is alſo encluded all thoſe for whom it is practiſed, for many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in theſe dayes cannot breake his Shinnes, haue his Noſe bleede, loſe a game at Cards, heare a Dogge howle, or a Cat wawle, but inſtantly they will runue to the Calculator, and haue him turne ouer his <hi>Ephemreides,</hi> and his Annuall Calenders, ſtuft full of lies and ſuperſtitious obſeruations. I will counſell all thoſe therefore, that would know their Fortunes,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>den<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>trium <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erum &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> to looke into that Euerlaſting Calender, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Bible, for the Aſtrology they ſhall learne there, neuer tels falſe, but will certifie them that the cauſe of their ill fortunes is their ſinnes; and the good, the Mercies of God: that will tell them of the true Nature of Summer, that is of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:12869:33"/>their Reſurrection and Saluation, and the true condition of Winter, that is Death and Damnation. If they ſtudy this booke, they will quickly learne to be excellent Calculators, and learne what will become of them if they doe ill, and what if they liue well, it will tell them the Cauſes and the Cures of euery diſeaſe that doth infect the Soule. Yet for all this, it is the true condition, rather ſuperſtition of the world, to put their confidence rather in Aſtrologicall fallacies, then in the Holy Ghoſts verities, drawing from the Starres the euents of future contingences, aſcribing what good ſoeuer befals vs to the influe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſom lucky Planet, &amp; not to Gods Mercies; &amp; what miſchief ſoeuer the to poſition of ſome ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuolent Starre, and not to our ſinnes, we put our confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in Aſtrologers, Starres, and Planets for a few experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and neuer hate them for their innumerable fallacie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> but this is eſpetially heredetary to women, becauſe by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion it came from their mother <hi>Eue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Why women eſpecially fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Figure-Caſters.</note> who by her vice of curioſitie or leuitie, or admirable facilitie rather then fatui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, was deceiued by the Serpent, in deſiring to know fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture things, which folly deſcends naturally to women, who will rather beleeue a Mathematician then a Diuine; ſo that theſe Calculators if among hundred errors they happen but vpon one truth, then without any ſuſpition they may lye a thouſand times after, yet theſe fooliſh,<note place="margin">Franciſ, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar.</note> credulous, and Appleeating women will beleeue them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sebaſtians confutation of Aſtrologers.</note> 
                  <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> that writ bitterly againſt Aſtrologers, ſayth, it is an Art againſt tke Law of God, and full of deceite and viliany: for ſayth hee, Goe to any Doctor of the Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matickes, and tell him thou haſt had very ill lucke all thy life time, and deſire him to tell thee vnder what Planet thou wert borne, and no doubt his anſwer will bee, that thou wert borne either vnder malitious <hi>Mars;</hi> or that <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> was Apoſtaticall and retrograde: when you haue beene with him, then goe to another and tell him that you haue had very good Fortune, and deſire him to tell
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12869:34"/>thee what Starre raigned at thy birth, and it will be very ſtrange, if he doe not tell thee as the firſt did, eyther vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Mars,</hi> or <hi>Saturne;</hi> who to proue himſelfe an Artiſt, will turne ouer huge Volumes, by which hee will ſhew, that it is neceſſarie that you muſt haue good fortune, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing borne vnder thoſe Starres the firſt ſaid were ill, and in a Circle drawne together in euery part, by which hee will take diuers and ſundrie occaſions to ſpeake any thing. Now if they chance to miſſe in their Praedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they haue a prettie euaſion to ſhunne the ſuſpition of Lying, which they draw from the interrogatorie part of Aſtrologie.</p>
               <p>The opinion of Aſtrologers is, when the mind of Man is ſpurred to the deſire of knowing any thing; that ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly it cannot be done by election, or conſultation, but the influence of a Conſtellation that houre conſiſting in Heauen. And when any man conſults with an Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, by a Figure in Heauen the houre of Interrogation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found out, the Aſtrologer can anſwer truely of any thing ſought for, or demaunded: As whether an abſent friend be aliue or dead; if a Legate or Meſſenger, that is ſent into any Countrey, ſhall returne home againe ſafe and well, and whether hee ſhall diſpatch that matter hee went about proſperouſly, and an innumerable many of other things, that humane curioſitie doth doubt of: to which ſometimes they may anſwer truely, although they often lye, and are neuer found fault with for it; for they haue found out a way, whereby they can ſufficiently excuſe themſelues to thoſe that are ignorant and ſimple in theſe things. For they ſay, That if any man, beeing doubtfull of any thing, doth with a naturall motion and radicall intention aske them any thing, that then they can reſolue them of any Queſtion they aske. Now if they miſſe, and cannot anſwer directly and truely to what was propounded to them, then they ſay, that hee
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12869:34"/>that askt that Queſtion, did it not with any naturall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or any firme or radicall intention to bee reſolued, but onely to trie their Art. Thus oftentimes they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, and are deceiued in their anſwers; not by any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect that is in their Art, but by the leuitie of him that did aske the Queſtion: and thus they excuſe themſelues. Which are meere tricks for euaſion, and haue no ground at all from reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Chaldaei Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logi Nabuch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n ſor ſommun dicere nequ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</note>But I admire what excuſe the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> and <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daean</hi> Aſtrologers could finde, when among ſuch an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of them, not one of them could truely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer touching the Dreames of <hi>Pharach</hi> and <hi>Nabuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar,</hi> when <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Daniel</hi> could anſwer directly? Doe you thinke this was done by any inſpection,<note place="margin">Egypttaci Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natores ſomm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Pharaonis dicere non pot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</note> or peeping into any Aſtrolobe, or obſeruing any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellation? No: for it was done by the reuelation of Almightie God; therefore it was paſt the Rules of your Art.</p>
               <p>There is another neat Deluſion, whereby they benefit themſelues very much; which is, by the obſeruations of the Heauens to know, if it be fit or conuenient for a man to trauell, or doe any other buſineſſe in: which is moſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious and diabolicall. For they will not haue a man eate, drinke, be merry, take Phyſicke, or trauell, marry, ioyne friendſhip, ſend forth a Meſſenger, buy, ſell, put on new Clothes, begin the Alchymiſts Worke, ſet Boyes to Schoole, goe to Law, Hawke, Hunt, Fiſh, or goe to the Bathe, but they will haue them doe it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome Conſtellation, and will ſet forth Rules when to doe theſe things, and when not. If they can doe theſe things, I wonder they doe not ſet forth a Rule, and chuſe an Houre and Conſtellation, vnder which a man may dye well, and auoid Hell fire, and enioy the ioyes of Heauen: but I thinke their Art hath nothing to doe with this.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:12869:35"/>
               <p>Yet I will not denye, but that the Influences of the Starres haue an operation in the differences of Bodyes: for what is more belonging to the Body, then to exerciſe Husbandry, to cut downe Timber for Building, while it is not too full of ſappe, and to obſerue the Times and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons when they ſhould be done?</p>
               <p>But thoſe obſeruers of time are to be laught at, that will not goe out of their Houſe before they haue had counſell of their Almanacke, and will rather haue the Houſe fall on their heads, then ſtirre, if they note ſome naturall effect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the motion of the Aire, which they ſuppoſe will varie the luckie blaſts of the Starres, that will not marry, or traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>ca inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitio <hi>26.</hi> q. c. <hi>7.</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>na Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> or doe the like, but vnder ſome Conſtellation. Theſe ſure are no Chriſtians: becauſe faithfull men ought not to doubt, that the Diuine Prouidence, from any part of the World, or from any Time whatſoeuer, is abſent. Therefore wee ſhould not impute any ſecular buſineſſe to the power of the Starres, but to know, that all things are diſpoſed by the arbitrement of the King of Kings.</p>
               <p>The Chriſtian Faith is violated, when ſo like a Pagan and Apoſtata any man doth obſerue thoſe dayes which are called <hi>Aegyptiaci,</hi> or the Calends of <hi>Ianuarie,</hi> or any Moneth, or Day, or Time, or Yeere, eyther to trauell, marry, or to doe any thing in: for whoſoeuer he be that beleeues theſe things, hath erred from the Chriſtian Faith and Baptiſme.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> in his <hi>Enchiridion</hi> ſayth, That it is a great offence for any man, to obſerue the time and courſe of the Moone when they plant any Trees, or ſowe any Corne: for he ſayth, none puts any truſt in them, but they that worſhip them, beleeuing there is ſome diuine power in them; thinking, that the poſition of ſome Star thought to haue an influence in them according to thoſe things they beleeue concerning the Natiuities of men. This me thinkes is moſt ſimple and ridiculous; for thus I will argue againſt them.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:12869:35"/>
               <p>If this be true which they hold, that it is good to ſowe Corne vnder ſuch a luckie Conſtellation, what is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then, that after the Corne that is ſcattered on the Earth by the laborious hands of the Husbandman, that after ſo much Graine is come vp together, looke greene together, ripen together, and fit for the Sickle, that ſome of it is blaſted, ſome quite choakt vp, ſome deuoured by Birds, ſome by Beaſts, ſome trodden downe, and ſome of the eares pluckt from their ſtalkes by men that come by that field they grow in? how comes it to paſſe then I ſay, that ſome of this ſhould goe ſafely into the Barne, and ſome of it againe be deuoured and ſpoyled? which mee thinkes ſhould not be, if the ſame Conſtellation vnder which it was ſowne, had but one Influence, which ſhould be good, and not a ſecond, which was bad.</p>
               <p>But I will now let theſe things paſſe (becauſe I make no doubt but I haue ſtrongly confuted them) and come to the laſt, but the wicked part of Aſtrologie; which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes the making of Aſtrologicall Images, and to what purpoſe they are made: where I will ſhew, they haue no force or vertue from any Starre or Conſtellation, but that the Deuill worketh about them, and in them, cauſing them to be made vnder a Conſtellation, that the impietie of their Idolatry may the more ſecretly be hid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The vanitie of Aſtrologers about <hi>their Images.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Fabricke of Aſtrologicall Images are made vnder a certaine Conſtellation, eyther to auoid hurtfull things, or to intice profitable things, for to diuers vſes they are made. Some are made for the deſtruction of ſome things: as if you would remoue a Scorpion from a place, you muſt carue the figure of ſome Scorpion either in Stone, Wood, or Iron, vnder ſome conuenient Conſtellation, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12869:36"/>inſcribe on it an effectuall Name, ſignifying the Name of the thing that is to be auoided, and the Name of the Signe aſcending, and of the like in diuers parts of the Image, with many other obſeruations, which for breuity ſake I will now let paſſe. For a contrary effect, you muſt haue a contrary Conſtellation, and a contrary Operation, as in the like I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages pertayning to Loue, Enmitie, Health, or the like. And although there are many effects cauſed by theſe Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,<note place="margin">Non virtus ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginis ſed opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio damonis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducit effectum.</note> as experience teacheth vs, yet they are miſerably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, that thinke it done by the vertue of any Conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when it is done by the meere operation of the Deuill: For not the vertue of the Image, but the operation of the Deuill, worketh the effect. And learned <hi>Auerroi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> writing againſt <hi>Algazel</hi> the Aſtrologer, ſayth, That theſe Images haue no vertue from the Starres, becauſe artificiall things are not capable of any influence, neyther are they any cauſe of a naturall operation: For Qualitie is in the Predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Actio.</hi> An Image therefore made of any earthly ſubſtance, is nothing but a maſſie Effigies, and capable of no Action.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A great vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note>And in like manner, thoſe Images that are buried in the midſt of the place where their operations are expected, are contrary to naturall reaſon. And other things that are obſerued in them, ſhew as great vanitie: as, when ſome mens Names muſt be written with the left hand, ſome with the right; ſome Images muſt be buried with their faces vpwards, ſome with their feet vpwards: which are all ſignes rather of a Compact with the Deuill, then any other natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall cauſe; as in the Negromanticke Images of Angels, or rather of their inſcription of Deuills, and other vnknowne Names and Characters.<note place="margin">A Compact with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</note> Alſo, the vſe of their Suffumigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Inuocations are ſignes of a Compact and League with the Deuill.</p>
               <p>The prodigious impietie of the <hi>Dominicke</hi> Fryers in the Fabricke of theſe Images, would make a Hiſtorie bigger then the <hi>Iliads:</hi> for they haue made by their Magicall tricks
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:12869:36"/>weeping Statues, by which they wrought many Miracles, which they learnt of the Prieſts of the Idols of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who haue deceiued many, as may appeare by the <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian</hi> Statues, deſtroyed by the Chriſtians: for when they ouerthrew the Phane of <hi>Syrapis,</hi> there were Images found both of Wood and Braſſe, whoſe inward parts were made hollow, and with inſtruments were faſtened to the Roofes of their Churches and Temples, from whence they ſpake.</p>
               <p>And ſince the time of Poperie, there haue beene found in Churches Images that haue had eyes put in by Art, that would weepe and let drops of bloud trickle downe their faces, ſweat bloud, and would twinckle with their eyes to the people by the helpe of inſtruments, and would wrythe their heads and neckes backward and forward, according to the will of the Prieſts that inuented them, to beguile the people, and to enrich themſelues. Theſe Puppets had no Tongues, but onely moued and ſtirred, making ſignes to the people, many of which, the Cardinalls erected, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned, and commended, to inſtruct the people: which were nothing but deceits and tricks of theſe holy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Fathers, ſtill to detaine the people in ignorance, and that they ſhould not ſmell out their knauerie.</p>
               <p>Alſo, many of theſe Scab-ſhin Fryers (when any rich man died, that had left their Abbeyes and Monaſteries nothing to feed their fat guts with) would place ſome of their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complices in a Vault they had made of purpoſe vnder the dead Mans Tombe: ſo that when any of his ſonnes or kindred came (as the cuſtome in thoſe times was) to pray for the Soule of their deceaſed father, or kinſman, they ſhould heare a dreadfull voyce vnder the Sepulchre, telling him, it was the Spirit of him that was but lately buryed there, and that his Soule could neuer be at reſt, while ſuch (the Fryers had moſt minde to) were giuen to the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie; ſo that the blind people beleeuing this to be the Spirit of their father, or kinſman, would inſtantly goe home, and confirme thoſe Lands on their Monaſterie.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12869:37"/>Thus poore ſoules, they were often deluded by ſuch coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit voyces of ſome ſubtill Fryer, or as knauiſh a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of their Fraternitie. Therefore if there be any in theſe dayes (eſpecially old Men and Women) that beleeue the Soules or Spirits of the dead walke, let them but reade the Scriptures, and they ſhall find it to be moſt falſe; for that affirmes, that the Soules of the good inſtantly goe to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and of the bad inſtantly to Hell; therefore their Spirits cannot wander. Againe, the Soule that is in Heauen minds no earthly matter; and it was neuer knowne, that any Soule euer returned out of Hell, for the Poets themſelues ſay, <hi>Nullus redditurus ab Orco.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But theſe Images and Tricks of the Fryers do but reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Statues of Negromancers, made with great toyle and labour.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Fryer</hi> Bacon. Albertus Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> For Fryer <hi>Bacon</hi> was many yeeres, before hee could make his Head ſpeake. And the Image of <hi>Albertus Magnus</hi> was to be wondred at, which hee made in the full and perfect ſhape of a Man, who with the Wheeles and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Engines that he had cunningly &amp; artificially wrought in it, made it ſpeake and pronounce words as diſtinctly, as if they did proceed from a man indued with ſence and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. This Statue,<note place="margin">Thomas Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas.</note> when <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> was ſent into his Chamber where it lay hid, heard it ſpeake very articulately: which when he heard, then looking for it, and finding it, and viewing it very ſeriouſly, at laſt ſtrucke it with a Club, and brake it all to pieces. Which when <hi>Albertus</hi> heard and ſaw, he cryed out and ſaid; <hi>Thomas,</hi> thou haſt deſtroyed the worke of thirtie yeeres labour and paines. Now can any man iudge, that either <hi>Bacon</hi> or <hi>Albertus</hi> made theſe vnder any Conſtellation, or that it ſpake by the influence of any Starre? if they doe, they are wretchedly deceiued: for it was either by a materiall Engine, or the Deuill that ſpake within them, brought into them by their Art. Therefore wee may perſwade our ſelues, that all theſe Images, made by the Art either of a Fryer or Negromancer, are vnlawfull to be made of them, or vſed of any other.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:12869:37"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Theſe Images lawfull.</note>But if we muſt allow any Statue or Image, they muſt be thoſe of <hi>Paſquil</hi> and <hi>Morphirius,</hi> on whoſe breſts were written no Lie-Bills, as the Popes called them, but True-Bills of their villanies. Theſe Statues were of ſtone, and the verſes carued on their breſts, were bitter and Satyricall, ſharply reuiling the Sorcery, Sodomitry, Symony, Inceſt,<note place="margin">Phil. Can. p. Medita c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Murther, Witchcraft, Poyſoning, and Sacriledge of the Popes and Cardinals, whereupon the Gentlemen of Rome wittily ſayd; That it was not lawful for men to ſpeake there vices, the ſtones did proclaym them. But pope <hi>Adrian</hi> would haue taken an order, and haue them flung into <hi>Tyber,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pope</hi> Adrian. Sueſſanus.</note> if <hi>Sueſſanus</hi> the Legate of <hi>Charles</hi> the Emperour who fauored them, had not preuented him: who ſayd to his Holineſſe, that if they were flung into <hi>Tyber</hi> the Crocodiles and Rats, and other monſtrous Serpents would catch them and ſing them: to which anſwer ſome report, the holy Father ſtood as mute as one of his Cardinals Mules; but ſome report that he began to be angry at <hi>Sueſſanus</hi> anſwer, and in a rage ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly ſayde, that he would haue them burnt, to whom the Legate wittily replyed againe, ſaying: If you burne theſe Images their aſhes will not be blowne through the citie, but into other countreys, ſo that the people will take occaſion to celebrate and reuerence thoſe Aſhes for the writing ſake, and ſo it will come to paſſe, that they being diſperſed throgh the world, the ſinnes of <hi>Rome</hi> will generally be knowne to all nations. At this ſecond anſwer, his Holineſſe wae more perplexed then before, and ſeeing he could doe no good, either by drowning or burning, hee bid them ſtand in the Deuills name. But I haue made too long a digreſſion, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will returne againe to our Negromancers, and now I haue ſpoken of their Images, I will briefly and plainely lay open the viperous generation of Negromancy, which are Idolatry, Diuination, and vaine obſeruaſion, with all the helliſh brood that proceeds from them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:12869:38"/>
               <head>The damnable ofspring of Negromancy.</head>
               <p>IDolatry is a Diuine Worſhip, attributted to Idols, which Idolls are Statues or Images which the Gentiles wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped with Diuine Honour,<note place="margin">Idolatry the daughter of Negromancy.</note> beleeuing there was ſome diuinitie in them, by reaſon of their anſwers and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full effects the Deuill wrought in them. Such were the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of <hi>Hermes Treſmegiſtus,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Mercurie,</hi> in which they did beleeue, that by a kinde of Art the ſoules of Deuills and Angels were encluded, vnder a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Conſtellation, which Diuinitie and Naturall Phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy doth reprehend: for they hold that a Spirit cannot poſſibly bee vegitable,<note place="margin">Notae. Ariſtotle de Anima.</note> or can ſubſtantially informe artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all bodyes: For the Soule, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, is an Act of a naturall body, not artificiall: for a man cannot by any matter, as Herbs, Wood, Stone, Words, or Conſtellation,, expell a good or bad Spirit, or being cald, that it can come preſently and dwell in an Idoll, becauſe corporall things cannot by any naturall order haue any operation in incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall things. There haue beene ſome of the Gentiles that haue not onely attributed Diuine honour to Statues and Images, but beleeued them to be Gods, for ſome vertue or magnitude of their Acts theſe Statues repreſented; as to <hi>Iupiter, Hercules, Venus,</hi> and the reſt, and other monſters of this kinde. Alſo they did not onely honour corporall, but incorporall things, as Intelligences, Angels, and the Soules of heauenly Bodyes, which they call <hi>Aeria Anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> and they did not ſeparate the ſoules of men from Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine honour, which is moſt diuelliſh. This kinde of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie at theſe dayes is vſed among our Antagoniſts the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, for they pray to Iron,<note place="margin">Papiſts.</note> Wood, Gold, Siluer, and wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Images, that haue neither ſight, feeling, ſence, life, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration in them, and haue as ſmall influence in them after are made, either by the Caruer, or Goldſmiths hand, as they
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12869:38"/>had when they firſt were in a maſſie lumpe, either in the Tree or Mine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Diuination, the 2. daughter of Negroman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. <hi>Iſidor lib. octa Etymologia.</hi>
                  </note>The ſecond daughter of ſuperſtition is Diuination, by which our Aſtrologers miſerably labour to know of future things, either good or bad. Theſe are they <hi>Iſidorus,</hi> ſaith, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port themſelues to be full of diuination, who by craft and deuice foretell of things to come, by the effects which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed vpon neceſſitie from cauſes, vnleſſe they are eſpecially hindered of God, certainly proceeding from the cauſe of nature: as the eclipſe of the Sunne and the Moone, and the effects which proceed from theſe cauſes may bee foretold of by as probable coniecture, as well as a Mariner may fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell of a ſtorme that will ariſe by a darke cloude, that is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before or behinde him. Haue not many olde women told by the vnhappy conditions of a boy that he would be hangd, and hath it not falne out right? Haue not many graue Matrons foretold, that young wanton Laſſes would proue Wagtails, &amp; hath it not come to paſſe? Haue not many men by the damnable tricks they haue ſeene in Catchpoles, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told that they would proue knaues, and hath it not beene true? yet theſe are but meere coniectures. Againe, Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers boaſt they can diuine, which is moſt falſe: for the Prophets themſelues foretelling future things by Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, did not diuine but Propheſie; for Diuination is alwayes taken in the worſt part, becauſe in it the operation of the Deuill doth alwayes come. For <hi>Bonauenture</hi> ſayth:<note place="margin">Bonauent. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> to aske counſell of the Deuill is a great miſchiefe. The <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> of diuination by which they can foretell of future things are many. Somtimes they do it by plaine inuocation of the deuill, who with their execrable Exorciſmes, Coniurations, Characters, and Figures, and diuers other ceremonies,<note place="margin">Praeſtigium.</note> and to ſpeake more truly, ſacrifices at diuers times doe call the deuill to giue them anſwers, who by diuers manners and formes appeare to them, who as ſubtilly and deceitfully doth anſwer to thoſe queſtions propounded to them, as may appeare by theſe examples.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:12869:39"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Papa Pater. Polyd. virg lib. <hi>5.</hi> de re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentione.</note>Pope <hi>Sylueſter</hi> the ſecond, that with ſmall learning had attained to his Pontificalibus, being greedy long to enioy that Sea, by this diuelliſh kinde of Coniuration rayſed vppe the Deuill, and askt his counſell how long he ſhould liue. To whom the Diuell anſwered, that if he did take heede of <hi>Hierulaſem</hi> he ſhould liue a long time. Pope <hi>Silueſter</hi> now thought himſelfe to be long liued, becauſe hee determined neuer to ſee <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> But foure yeere after he came to his Pallace of <hi>Sanctae Crucis,</hi> he lay in a chamber vnknown to himſelfe, called <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> then inſtantly being mindful of the Deuils anſwer, he ſayd that hee ſhould, as hee did not liue long after.</p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth, whom the Deuill did helpe to his Popedome,<note place="margin">Guicciard.</note> promiſing him that he ſhould liue <hi>Decem et Octo</hi> in his Popedome, vpon compoſition that he would be his after that time was expired. Now theſe numbers were ouer generally expounded of <hi>Alexander</hi> touching his yeers, for he ſuppoſed the Deuil meant by Nine and Ten nineteen yeeres, when the Deuill meant but nine yeeres and tenne months,<note place="margin">Octo &amp; decem.</note> which was much about the time he came to claim his right of the holy Father.</p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>Albertus Scotus</hi> doubting of his Fortunes, rayſed vp the Deuill,<note place="margin">Lord of <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia.</hi>
                  </note> and asked him concerning the ſecuritie of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his ſtate, to whom the Deuill thus ſubtilly and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricately anſwered; <hi>Domine ſtes ſecurus, inimici tui ſuauiter intrabunt terram et ſubijcientur Domui tui,</hi> which as the words now lye, beare this interpretation in Engliſh. Sir you ſhall ſtand ſecure, thy enemies ſhall peaceably enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy kingdome, but ſhall be ſubiect to thy houſe. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he did hope well of this anſwer, and made no doubt of the victory; but the Deuil did not promiſe him the victory, but the ouerthrow, and meant thus. <hi>Domine ſtes ſecurus,</hi> ſo did diuide the word <hi>Domine</hi> into <hi>Domine,</hi> againe, <hi>Inimici tui ſua vi ter intrabunt terram et ſubijcient vr,</hi> that is, <hi>Ignem Domui tui;</hi> ſo the Deuill did expound it, thus any man elſe would doe the ſyllables, being ſo deuided and out a
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:12869:39"/>peeces. Thou ſhalt not ſtand ſecure at home, thy enemies three times with their forces ſhall enter vpon thy land, and ſhall ouercome with fire, and ſo was <hi>Albertus</hi> deluded.</p>
               <p>Alſo the Oracles of <hi>Apollo</hi> were but meere witchcrafts and deluſions of the Deuill,<note place="margin">Oracula.</note> giuing anſwers from a hollow place of the Temple, after the Prieſts had ſacrificed to him, who did moſt commonly ſpeake nothing but <hi>Amphibologias nodoſas et flexiloqua reſponſa,</hi> deceiuing many that came to it, becauſe his anſwer did ſtill include a double ſence: ſo that if a man did reade ouer all <hi>Chryſippus</hi> volumes, concerning the Oracle of <hi>Apollo,</hi> he ſhould not finde one anſwer but did include at wofold meaning, of which I thinke it not imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to remember two or three of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Francis Petrarch</hi> maketh mention in his Moralls that <hi>Nero</hi> asking counſell of <hi>Apollo</hi> at <hi>Delphos,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Franc. Petrarc. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Mora.</note> deſiring to know how long he ſhould liue: this anſwer was made him that if he did take heed of ſeuentie three yeeres, hee ſhould liue a long time. When <hi>Nero</hi> did heare this anſwer, ſuch a ſecuritie did rocke him a ſleepe, that fearing nothing, he did glut him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in delight, becauſe hee thought hee ſhould not die before the prefixed time of the Oracle, ſo that his minde was rauiſhed downe the ſwift torrent of an inſolent vanity and vaine inſolency, pampering himſelfe with high dyet, muſicke, and delights that pleaſe his ſences, but beeing in the Meridian of his happineſſe, in a minute he was flung downe into the dungeon of diſgrace, for he heard the popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar voyce curſe the name of <hi>Nero,</hi> and celebrate the name of <hi>Galba,</hi> by whom he was diſceptered, and who at that time was iuſt ſeuentie and three yeeres of age.</p>
               <p>But one of the prettieſt trickes the Deuill playde by his Oracle, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alerius Maximas</hi> makes mention of:<note place="margin">Valer. Maxim.</note> for hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth that a Sophiſter to make himſelfe merry, came to laugh at the Oracle of <hi>Apollo</hi> in <hi>Delphos,</hi> and askt him if hee ſhould find his horſe he had loſt. To whom the Oracle an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that he ſhould find his horſe againe, but if he did not take heed, hee would take him ſuch a kicke that would
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:12869:40"/>breake his necke. At this anſwer of the Oracle, the Sophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter went away laughing, becauſe it promiſed him to finde a horſe he neuer loſt. But as he trauelled into his owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, he fell into the hands of king <hi>Attalus,</hi> to whom in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time he had done ſome wrong, and was by him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be ſet vpon a ſtone called <hi>Equus</hi> a horſe,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i nomen erat Eq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> from whence he was flung headlong downe and brake his neck, fulfilling the Oracle of <hi>Apollo.</hi> Thus much for the Deuill and his Oracles, which alwayes were ſome ſuch cunning deluſions, whoſe end was commonly miſchiefe.</p>
               <p>Somtime you do diuine by dreames,<note place="margin">Somniu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and that is called <hi>per Somnia.</hi> Naturall Phyloſophy and Diuinity doe manifeſt the cauſe of dreames: dreames ſometime proceed from the fulnes of the belly, ſomtimes from the emptines of the belly, ſomtimes by illuſion, ſomtimes by reuelation, &amp; ſometimes by cogitation and reuelation.<note place="margin">Melancholy. Chollericke. Phlegmaticke Sanguine.</note> Alſo the diuers habitudes of the body doth adminiſter diuers cauſes of dreames: ſo that melancholy men often dreame of horrible and fearefull ſhapes and formes of deuills. Chollericke men, of cutting throates, of quarrells, of ſtratagems, and firing of Citties. Phlegmaticke men often dreame that they are in feare of drowning, and ſometimes dreame a ſweeter dreame then this, that they are eating of hony, which is cauſed by the Phlegme which is naturally ſweete, diſtilling to the pallate of the mouth.<note place="margin">Incubus morbus noctu quteſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in feſtans quum ſcilicet externa quaeda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vis quieſcentes videtur euade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re &amp; veluti ſuo pondore preſſos graeuare Naſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur hoc morbi genus copia va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum ex vora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitare &amp; crudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in caput re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundantium.</note> The Sanguine complexion, from the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of blood, cauſeth men to dreame of the <hi>Incubus,</hi> which Phyſitians hold is the cauſe of a future <hi>Apoplexie:</hi> And that is the reaſon that many ignorant people that are of ſanguine complexion, and feed on fleſh, egges, veale, and drink wine and ſuch like, which cauſeth blood, that beleeue that in their ſleepes they often feele the Night-mare, or an <hi>Incubus,</hi> which is nothing elſe but a diſeaſe ariſing of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pors, diſturbing thoſe that are at repoſe in the night, whoſe externall force doth ſeeme to euade their ſences, and to preſſe their bodyes with their ponderous weight, and this is the reaſon that Phiſitians hold that the <hi>Incubus</hi> is a ſign of a future <hi>Apoplexie,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Apoplexie</hi> is a ſtupefaction of the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12869:40"/>Nerues in the whole body, with a priuation of the ſence and motion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Apoplexia, ſlu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pefactio neruo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum totius cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris cum pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatione ſenſus &amp; motus, a verbo Graeco, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. quod eſt percuti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> attonitum reddo.</note>Againe, ſome hold that the cauſe of dreames ariſeth from the buſineſſe and affaires a man is moſt imployed in the day time, ſo that the impreſſion of them ſticking in the Table of the Fantaſie, makes a man dream of thoſe things in the night which he hath done in the day, as for example. Men giuen to drinke much, often dreame that they are in the bottome of ſome noble mans ſeller drinking of healths. And men according to their employments dreame of their buſineſſe ouer night. Your Lawyer he dreames of Angels, a moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed dreame, and if he chance to talke in his ſleepe, it is moſt commonly of Demurs, Habeas Corpuſſes, Siſſararas, Writs, Latitats, and Procidendos. The Phiſitian he dreames of a great Plague, and if he talks, it is of nothing but Purgations, Vomits, Gliſters, and Pills. I knew a Player dreamt that his braines were beaten out with the Corke of groate Bottle of Ale, and as he was ſpeaking the Prologue it hiſt at him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſpake it ſo ſcuruily. The Cutpurſe and the Catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pole moſt commonly dreame of a Michaelmas Terme, for that is their beſt time to picke pockets and cheat in; and ſo of all the reſt according to their imployments: therefore this makes mee not of <hi>Symonides</hi> opinion, who held that all dreames are ſent from God, which all honeſt men will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, becauſe they know that God is not the author of any ill. Again, dogs and kine dream, eſpecially when they haue loſt their whelps or calues, who ſuddenly will wake out of their ſleeps, &amp; run howling &amp; lowing into diuers places to finde them. Nor muſt we beleeue theſe Negromancers in their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelliſh worke of working in our Fantaſies by dreames, that they can doe any thing that is true, as when they cauſe vs dream of gold, or ſiluer, &amp; we chance to find it inſtantly, to affirme with many old women that all dreames are true, for this is but a tricke of the deuill to bring vs into ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: which tricke is not much vnlike that he hath put vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Papiſts, making them beleeue that at the ſight of the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12869:41"/>Croſſe he cannot be in quiet, but muſt flie away from it, but there is no true Chriſtian will thinke that the Deuill is afrayd of a peece of wood, gold, or ſiluer, but flyes from the Croſſe of purpoſe to draw them into the ſuperſtition of adoring the croſſe,<note place="margin">The Deuills tricke in flying from the croſſe</note> and kneeling to it inſtead of adoring him that once hung on the Croſſe, for although it bee a Croſſe, yet it hath no more vertue and influence in it then when it was a peece of wood, ſtone, or ſiluer.</p>
               <p>Thus then you ſee we muſt truſt to no dreams, except they come by the inſpiration of God and the Holy Ghoſt: of which God ſpake in the 12. of <hi>Numbers. I will ſpeake to him in a dreame,</hi> this was now by a good Angell, that God war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to flye into <hi>Aegypt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And oftentimes God ſuffereth the Euill Angel to delude the minds of men,<note place="margin">The euill An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell.</note> ſo that many times they haue beene ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetting with gallant Ladies, and by the phantaſticall illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Deuill, thinke that they haue beene in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of diuers women that rid on the backs of Cats, Dogs, Hogs, or that they haue beene ſayling on the maine Sea in ſhips no bigger then egge ſhells, &amp; that in the peace of mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night they haue trauelled through many parts of the world. Holy <hi>Iob</hi> prayeth againſt ſuch illuſions, ſaying: Thou doeſt terryfie me by dreames, and doſt ſhake me with horror by viſions.</p>
               <p>There are many Monks as the Golden Legend teſtifies,<note place="margin">S. <hi>Dominicus.</hi>
                  </note> that report this of their holy S. <hi>Dominicus,</hi> that his mother before he was borne dreamt that ſhe bare a huge dog in her wombe, holding a burning firebrand in his mouth, who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering into the world ſet it on fire. This dreame the holy Monkes did thus expound: that the viſion was not vaine ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Preachers in the Scriptures are called Dogs. But I will giue then a truer expoſition then this, not ſparing their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Order. It was certaine that this <hi>Dominicke</hi> was the author of one of the foure Mendicant Orders, and the firſt that found out the burning and firing of the Profeſſors of the Goſpell.</p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:12869:41"/>
               <p>Therefore his Imitators haue peculiarly challenged to themſelues the Inquiſition, and many other ſuch places, to exerciſe their Fire and Sword. And ſo by this was ſignified the burning Fire-brand <hi>Dominicus</hi> held in his mouth; by which an infinite company of godly men were conſumed into aſhes.</p>
               <p>Thus by this Dreame did the Deuill delude <hi>Dominicus</hi> Mother, and many more that did beleeue the interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it by the Monks. But in generall, Dreames are not to be beleeued: for they are moſt wicked and odious in the ſight of God, that thinke ſo; as may appeare in the 19. of <hi>Leuiticus, Deutronomie</hi> the 23. <hi>Ibidem</hi> 18. <hi>Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticus</hi> 24. and many other places of the Scripture. Thus much for your Diuination by Dreames.</p>
               <p>Sometimes they doe diuine by a Spirit;<note place="margin">Pythoniſſa.</note> and that is called <hi>Pythoniſſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometimes they anſwer to that they are called for, by diuers Figures Men or Women ſet in poliſht Stone, Iron, Braſſe, Steele, Glaſſe, or the Nayles of ones hand; and this is called by the generall Name of <hi>Geomancie:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Geomancie</note> And moſt commonly to ſuch as theſe, they chuſe out Women and Children. And I my ſelfe haue knowne many old Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men old Dogge at this kind of Diuination; who hold, that if the Nayles of the Hand grow yellow, it is a great ſigne of ill lucke, and that ſpecks are the true ſignes of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ill lucke.</p>
               <p>If theſe apparitions appeare in the Water, then it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Hydromancie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hydromancie.</note> Theſe I haue heard are very incident to Catch-poies, Bum-baylies, and the like, when they are duckt vnder Water at a high Tyde at one of the <hi>Temples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If theſe apparitions are in the Ayre,<note place="margin">Aeromancie.</note> then it is called <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romancie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If in the Fire, <hi>Pyromancie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pyromancie.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If by the bowels of Beaſts, offered vp on Altars to the Deuill, it is called <hi>Aruſpicium.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aruſpicium.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:12869:42"/>
               <p>But if by Incantations the Deuill ſeemes to riſe and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Queſtions propounded to them, then it is called <hi>Negromancie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Negromancie.</note> In this worſt Superſtition, Bloud is alſo v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: and the Reaſon <hi>Iſidorus</hi> giues, is this, becauſe he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth Diuine Worſhip; for in the Old Law, Bloud was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vp to God.</p>
               <p>If by the chattering of Birds, or by the voyce of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Creatures, they fore-tell of things to come, it is called <hi>Augurie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Augurie.</note> This kind of Diuination is moſt blaſphemous, odious, and againſt the honour of God. For they fayne, that with a Diuine inſtinct, Birds, and Fowles, with their Motions, Chatterings, Croakings, Winding, or fore-right flying, portend eyther good or bad lucke: which the Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks themſelues did laught at,<note place="margin">Homer. Iliad. <hi>2.</hi> Polydamantus.</note> and contemne. For <hi>Hector</hi> in <hi>Homer</hi> ſharpely reproued <hi>Polydamantus,</hi> who delayed his fight, expecting an Augurie: to whom <hi>Hector</hi> ſaid, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num eſſe Augurium optimum, Patriam fortiter defendere;</hi> There is one Augurie which is the beſt, ſtoutly to defend thy Countrey.</p>
               <p>Alſo this kind of Diuination was very frequent among the <hi>Iewes,</hi> and was laught and croſt by that learned and couragious <hi>Iew, Moſſolamus:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Moſſolamus. Ioſeph. Antiq. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> who being in the Warres, was told by an Aſtrologer, that hee ſhould march no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, vntill he had receiued an Augurie from the next Bird hee ſhould ſee come flying ouer his Army. But the <hi>Iew</hi> ſcorn'd the helpe of the Bird, and laught at the skill of the Southſayer, inſtantly taking his Bow in his hand, and as the Bird came croaking ouer the Army, ſlew it, then ſpake theſe words: Doeſt thou thinke, thou ſuperſtitious South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayer, that this Bird, ignorant of her owne ſafetie, could tell of the euent of our Warres? if it could haue fore-told of things to come, it would neuer haue come nigh this place, to be ſlaine of <hi>Moſſolamus</hi> the <hi>Iew.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If they fore-tell of things to come, by the moouing of diuers Members of Beaſts;<note place="margin">Auſpicium.</note> then it is called <hi>Auspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:12869:42"/>
               <p>Alſo, when a man ſpeakes any thing to another without any intention, and as it were in ieaſt: as to ſay, hee will be hang'd, drown'd, kill'd, or the like; if this come to paſſe, then they call it, <hi>Omen.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Omen.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If they fore-tell of things that ſhall happen by ſignes that they ſee in the Lines of a mans hand;<note place="margin">Chyromancie.</note> then it is called <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romancie.</hi> This Art many old Women are learnedly expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienced in, and will tell any Man or Woman, for meat, drinke, or money, what ſhall befall them.</p>
               <p>If they fore-tell of any thing that ſhall happen by the ſignes they ſee in the ſhoulder-blades of Beaſts; then it is called <hi>Spatalmancia.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Spatalmancia.</note>
               </p>
               <p>There is alſo another kind of Diuination, which is by Lots: which Lots are made,<note place="margin">Sortilegium.</note> by drawing out points of an vncertaine number, with their faces turned towards the Moone, with other obſeruations to as little purpoſe as this. The <hi>Dutchmen</hi> are very skilfull at this, and haue couſened the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of infinite Maſſes of Money, by their ſelling of Papers: ſo that there was not one among forty, though he came neuer ſo merry to the Lotterie, but he ſhould be ſure to goe away Blanke.</p>
               <p>Thus Sir haue I layed forth the Brood of Diuination: Now I will come to the Obſeruations. It is a diſputable queſtion, whether by words or deeds the Deuill will be compelled by Negromancers, or whether being called by them, they come, becauſe of ſome league that is betweene them? If Deuils appeare, forced by Negromantick Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafes, why do not Negromancers make them come againſt their wills? which ſure they cannot: which is a ſigne, that there is a league and couenant concluded between the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill and Coniurers eyther manifeſt or occult, why elſe doe Negromancers dedicate their Bookes to the chiefe Deuills, whoſe name they often vſe, but only to make a couenant with the Deuill, that when they call them by thoſe Names, Charmes, Characters, Exorciſmes, and the like, they may appeare themſelues, or ſend ſome of their inferior Deuills as ſoone as they heare them.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:12869:43"/>
               <p>Theſe then are approued ſignes and markes of a Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant: And that the Spirits may ſhew themſelues to haue a greater power, ſometimes they ſeeme very vnwilling to come, eyther becauſe they would make the Inchanter more zealous, or that he may delude ſimple people: for hee is a Lyar, and the Father of Lyes.</p>
               <p>And now I hope it will not be impertinent to confute the Opinion of many,<note place="margin">Digreſsion.</note> who will not beleeue, that there are any Deuils but thoſe that are in Hell: but I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that in euery corner there is a Spirit; and beſides that, amongſt vs there are Fierie, Ayrie, Earthie, and Watrie Spirits.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Roaring Boy, <hi>ae</hi> Salamander.</note>The Fierie Deuill, is your Roaring Boy, that like a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamander liues moſt commonly by Fire; Smoake is the chiefeſt nouriſhment hee hath: hee is a ſwearing Raſcall, that with the hot Oathes he ſpues out from the Canon of his mouth, is able to burne, if not his owne, yet their lippes that ſtand by them. This Spirit is moſt commonly reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in Tobacco Shops, Hot-Water Shops, Tauernes, Brothels, and ſuch Places: and the onely Negromancer to coniure downe this Deuill, is (if he begins to roare or ſpit fire) ſome euerlaſting Conſtable, or new-elected Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, that deſires to be knowne a Man in his Office, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome Iuſtice of Peace; who can ſeldome or neuer make him quiet, while they haue charm'd them into the ſmall Circumference of a Compter.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pick-pocket, <hi>a</hi> Camelion.</note>The ſecond, is your fine <hi>Mercurian</hi> finger'd Cutpurſe, that like a Camelion liues on the Ayre of his Inuention, or indeede like the Ayre fills euery place. This Spirit haunts Play-houſes, Cock-pits, Tiltings, Prizes, <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster</hi> in the Terme-time, and ſuch fertile places, from whence they gleane a fruitfull Crop, to maintaine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. The onely Coniurer to lay this Spirit (if he be too turbulent) is <hi>Porredge,</hi> or <hi>Pulman,</hi> who neuer leaue char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming them, while they haue layd them vnder the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:12869:43"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pyrate, <hi>a</hi> Herring.</note>The third is your Watrie Spirit, who liues by the ſalt Water like a Herring; and this is your Pyrat, that liues on the ſpoyle of all Countries. This Spirit is reſident about <hi>Barbarie,</hi> the <hi>Straits</hi> mouth, ſometimes about the <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Iriſh</hi> Coaſts. The only Charme that muſt bind this Deuill, is a Letter of Mart, which moſt commonly brings them as farre as S. <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Waterings,</hi> or <hi>Wapping,</hi> and at the laſt Caſt leaues them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vſurer, <hi>a</hi> Mole.</note>The fourth and laſt Deuill is your earthy Deuill, and he is an Vſurer, that like a Mole feedes on the bowels of the Earth, as Siluer and Gold. This Spirit is moſt frequent in Scriueners ſhops, putting out money to vſe, or at the Paper-Houſes of both the Compters, entring Actions: and there is nothing can lay this Spirit ſo well, if he begins to be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious, as a <hi>Priuy Seale</hi> to borrow money of him, or a <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poena</hi> out of the Exchequer, for extortion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Errant qui Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolos non eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ales ſpiritus ſed prauos hominum affectus eſſe fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt. Quomod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> enim Auaritia, Ambitio, Crud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litas, Perfidia, in Porcos demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graſſe. Matth, cap. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note>Beſides theſe Deuils, there are infinite many more in the Citie: as you ſhall ſeldome goe into <hi>Turne-bole-ſtreet,</hi> but there you ſhall ſee a three-chin'd Bawd or Whore ſitting in an Euening, inticing young men to ſinne, and is not this a deuilliſh tricke? You ſhall ſeldome goe into <hi>Cheape-ſide, Lombard-ſtreet,</hi> the <hi>Strand,</hi> or <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> but you ſhall ſee ſome Spirits, in the likeneſſe of Marchants, Goldſmiths, and Silke-mens Wiues, wearing moſt prodigious Hornes on their heads like a halfe Moone, the embleme of Change and Mutabilitie: you cannot walke into <hi>Houndſ-ditch, Charter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe Lane,</hi> or <hi>Long Lane,</hi> but you ſhall ſee Spirits ſtanding at moſt of thoſe dores, in the likeneſſe of griping Brokers. But of all Spirits that are familiar in the Citie, thoſe that ſtand before both the Compters, are the horribleſt &amp; feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt to men in debt, who appeare in the ſhapes of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geants, <hi>alias</hi> Varlets.</p>
               <p>Many other viſible Spirits there are in the World, which for breuitie ſake I will omit, becauſe I meane to proceed a little farther, and ſhew, why vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a certaine Conſtellation at certaine times, and in certaine terrible places, Apparitions
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:12869:44"/>appeare rather to Women &amp; Children, rather then to Men. Such matters as Coniurers vſe, do not compell Deuills, but rather are ſignes of a league compacted betweene them: For as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth, the Deuills take their habitations in bodyes that God,<note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uit. Dei.</note> not themſelues, created; and are deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in ſeuerall bodyes for varietie ſake, not as creatures with Aliment, but as Spirits with ſignes, which ſignes are delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in varietie: as ſometimes by Stones, Hearbes, Wood, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Creatures, Verſes, &amp; Rites; and men are often delighted with theſe things. Which the Deuil perceiuing, ſeduce them either by ſubtill or craftie meanes, or by apparances, in faw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and friend-ſeeming ſhewes, or beautifull and amiable ſhapes, as they haue appeared to ſome men in the formes of <hi>Lamiae,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m. de Orig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linguae Latinae.</note> which are but meere <hi>Phantaſma's</hi> of faire women ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing in that beautious ſhape, fayning themſelues to be in loue with young men, who haue beene ſo often conuerſant with them, that at the laſt they haue brought them to deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. But I thinke there are few <hi>Lamiae</hi> in theſe dayes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, except they be ſubſtantiall ones, which are Whores, who well may be compared to theſe Midnight Deluſions; for they will profeſſe loue, and neuer leaue a man, while they haue brought him to ſome Hoſpitall.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſubtletie of the Deuill.</note>Neither could the Deuil do theſe things, but that he pryeth into the heart of man, and then feeds them with that which moſt delights them. <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Aquin</hi> teacheth, that by theſe corporall things they can the more eaſily bring to effect that to which they are called, and they deſire this, that their Art might be held more admirable: And for this cauſe, being called vnder any Conſtellation, they rather will appeare.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Phantaſticall illuſions of the Deuill.</note>But why to Virgins, Children, and ſuch weake Creatures doe ſuch appearances ſhew themſelues more then to others, but that they may bring them into an opinion of their Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and that praeſtigious Witchcrafts and Deluſions may ſooneſt tempt them that haue the weakeſt faith? And to make them afraid, they appeare in the night as it were in hollow Caues and Cauernes of the Earth, Deſarts, darke, and
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:12869:44"/>ſolitarie Chambers, whereby the feare of theſe melancholy places, and the vnſeaſonable time of the appearance of the Deuill, may the more terrifie them. Thus the policie of the Deuill ſtill works on the weakeſt and ſillieſt kind of people.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Auecine <hi>6.</hi> de Natura.</note> 
                  <hi>Auecine</hi> ſhewes how the ſences may be deluded. The ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall means is this: Spirits worke nothing <hi>extra nos,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vs; for it is eaſie for Spirits to make many bodies of the Aire, which earthy bodies may wonder at.<note place="margin">In Epicure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> For <hi>Eraſmus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports a pretty piece of Magick performed by a <hi>Roman</hi> Prieſt (who had it not out of any place of the Scripture I am ſure) that inuited a company of Ladies to a Banquet, bidding them bring good ſtomackes with them.<note place="margin">Naturall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicke.</note> The Ladies came, were welcommed by him, entertained with delicate Muſicke, and ſeated at the Table according to their births. There were ſuch varietie of rare and ſtrange Diſhes, that they thought that others, not their owne Nation, did furniſh their Table: they eat well, drunke well, &amp; were merry; and which is better then a piece of Cheeſe, Pippins, or Carrowayes, to cloſe vp the mouth of the ſtomack after ſupper, they were all welcome. When this Feaſt, rather this Faſt was ended, and (which is not very vſuall with Courtiers) Grace being ſaid, they rendred the Prieſt heartie thanks for their Banquet, and went home. But they had not bin there at the moſt halfe an houre, but their ſtomacks began to call vpon them for meat, for they were all as hungry as if they had eat nothing at the Banquet: therfore did much wonder at themſelues, that they ſhould haue ſuch a great deſire to meat, ſeeing they did but newly come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch a royall entertainment. But this quaint deluſion the Prieſt afterward reuealed to them: for although he inuited them to a Feaſt, yet they had neuer a bit of meat; for his Art did delude both the Eye, that thought it ſaw ſuch things, and the Pallat, that ſeemed to taſte thoſe delicates.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">I haue ſeene this done in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> by a Iugler with a lame legge.</note>I my ſelfe haue ſeene a fellow, that would make people belieue, that they ſaw Orange trees ſpring out of his forhead, hauing Birds ſit and ſing on the boughes, which in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant would vaniſh away againe. This fellow was at <hi>Cambridge</hi> drinking at the Dolphin, and made a Drawer
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:12869:45"/>that fill'd him bad Wine, beleeue, that he would geld him if he would not bring him of the beſt Claret in the Cellar: which the Drawer laught at, and the more to croſſe him, fetcht of the worſt he could finde. This Iuggler ſwore he would be euen with him before long: but the Drawer went away laughing, bidding him do his worſt. But the Conceit came at the laſt, like a leſt in the laſt Lines of an Epigram: for when the Drawer leaſt thought of it, as hee was running downe ſtayres to fetch Wine, hee felt ſomething trickle downe his thighs, at the firſt thinking it had bin ſome Wine he had ſpilt on his breeches, but putting his hands into his Hoſe, hee pull'd them out bloudy againe; ſo that hee came running vp ſtayres, and with a wide mouth came roaring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Roome where we were drinking, crying, the lame man had gelt him, and that he was vtterly vndone. At the firſt this <hi>Vox exclamantis</hi> did beget ſuch a laughter in vs, that we were not able to ſpeake to him: but yet at the laſt, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the fellow good words, and good Wine, he made him a perfect man againe. This was but deceiuing of the ſences, and ſo not done, or if done, the worke of the Deuill.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rhodoginus</hi> makes mention of one <hi>Syreneus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rhodog. lib.</hi> 9.</note> that would run his Horſe a ſtrawes bredth a mile together, and make him amble, curuet, trot, pace, and gallop within the compaſle of a Buſhell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martin Berrhaus</hi> reports,<note place="margin">Martin Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhaus.</note> that he ſaw a Dancer carry two men on his ſhoulders, two on his armes, and one vpon his neck, yet would dance and vaut with ſuch agilitie, that a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boone with his drinking glaſſe could not tumble nimbler.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rhodoginus</hi> and <hi>Eraſmus</hi> makes mention of an <hi>Indian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rhodog. lib. <hi>12.</hi> cap. <hi>40.</hi> Eraſm. Apothe.</note> that by a tricke he had learnt of a Witch, would ſhoot through the narrow circumference of a ſmall Hoope-ring, ſtanding a furlong off.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iulius Paſcarius</hi> reports,<note place="margin">Iulius Paſca<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>. lib. <hi>2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. 2.</hi>
                  </note> that a Dice-player (who comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that after he was dead, his skin ſhould be made a Carpet for Gameſters to play on, his bones Dice to play with, and Treſſels for ſtooles to ſit on) by a Magicall tricke he had, would cheat the moſt cheatingſt Gameſter.</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:12869:45"/>
               <p>Therefore, if theſe that are but <hi>Mataeotechnia,</hi> vaine imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Art, ſeeme ſo wonderfull to people beholding them on Stages &amp; Theaters: how leſſe miraculous is it, if the deuill by Elements can make ſtranger apparances, or by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret inſpirations delude the ſence, by framing the Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſmes of Images, by which he will deceiue men running, ſleeping, or walking?</p>
               <p>Why may not theſe Spirits be turnd into as many ſhapes as <hi>Diomedes</hi> companions were,<note place="margin">Phan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſmata.</note> that were in the Iland cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Diomede,</hi> not farre from the mountaine <hi>Garganus,</hi> that is in <hi>Apulea?</hi> Why not as well as <hi>Vliſſes</hi> companions, that were turned into beaſts, and whom <hi>Circes</hi> the famous Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cereſſe inchanted? Why not as well as the <hi>Arcadians,</hi> that were turnd into Wolues?<note place="margin">All theſe were but fictions or Phantaſmes.</note> Why may not there be a tranſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in theſe incorporeall ſpirits, as in theſe terreſtrial bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes? And why may not there be as ſtrange <hi>Metamorphoſis</hi> in theſe dayes, as there was in the dayes of <hi>Ouid</hi> and <hi>Varro?</hi> nay I will ſtand to it, that in theſe dayes there are as maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous changes and more true, for I haue knowne a Gallant that at the age of fiueteene, hath beene a pregnant wittie youth, but before twenty he hath beene turned into a right <hi>Aſinego.</hi> There haue beene many Citizens that haue beene very hanſome perſonable men in the morning, who before the Exchange hath bin done, hath bin turnd into monſtrous beaſts. There are many tradeſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that at their firſt ſetting vp haue beene very honeſt men, but after the third or fourth breaking, haue beene turnd into moſt fearefull Sergeants. I haue knowne many that haue beene accounted wiſe fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes in the Vniuerſitie, that haue no ſooner peept into the Temples, or one of the Innes of Court, but haue bin tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formd into monſtrous Aſſes. Then ſeeing there is ſuch a tranſmutation in earthly bodyes, why ſhould wee thinke it ſo ſtrange and rare in incorpor? all ſpiritse Yet theſe and the like are not recited as if they were true, but to ſhew how the ſences may bee deluded. And the like may appeare by thoſe women that oftentimes are perſwaded that they are riding on the backes of beaſts.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:12869:46"/>
               <p>Yet for all this, I will not grant there is any vertue in the words or charmes of a Negromancer to rayſe vppe theſe formes. Alſo there is no vertue in thoſe ceremoniall Exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſmes, with which Prieſts exorciſe Wine, Salt, Water, and the like, which I will manifeſtly ſhew you.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Three hard bones for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologers to gnaw on.</note>Firſt, in reſpect of the Matter, for the Matter is but Ayre, or Water, or Inke; which can haue no vertue in them, for by that reaſon, euery ſubſtance of the like kinde ſhould haue the ſame vertue.</p>
               <p>Secondly, in reſpect of the Accidental Form, which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a Configuration of diuers Characters, either in writing or ſpeaking, for Phyloſophy teacheth that Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall Formes haue no Action of themſelues.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in reſpect of the thing ſignified, as the word fire to burne this Paper, or the word Death to kill this Man, or the word God, to ſaue this Soule, or to raiſe vp any dead body; which cannot be: for the name of God cannot do it. But God muſt be inuocated by true Faith, whereby he is often pleaſed to grant our requeſts.<note place="margin">Note.</note> But Coniurers and Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers vſe the name of God in another kinde, and other Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, which rather driue away diuine Grace and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue then procure it, and ſo much the more they ſin, by how much the more they take the name of God in vaine, and to the worſhip of the Deuill. Therefore to conclude this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of Diuination, I will proue both by the Diuine, Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, and Canon Law, that it is not lawfull to be vſed.</p>
               <p>The Diuine Law ſayth:<note place="margin">Diuine Law. <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. <hi>Leuit.</hi> 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſuffer ſuch Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors to liue.</hi> A man or a woman in whom the Spirit of Diuination is found, let them dye the death: Let them bee ſtoned to death, and let their bloods bee vpon their owne heads. Alſo the Holy Ghoſt in another place ſayth: Let that Soule that is inclined to Southſayers be ſlaine in the midſt of the people.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Imperiall Law</hi> Canon extra de ſortilegiis per tot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. <hi>Vaine obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</hi>
                  </note> The Imperiall Law commands, that they ſhould be beheaded, or be put to any kinde of puniſhment the Iudge ſhall thinke moſt conuenient and fitting.</p>
               <p>The third daughter of Superſtition is vaine Obſeruation,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:12869:46"/>which teacheth to know future things either good or bad, as to tell whether a man condemned to be hangd, ſhall dye that death or no, which is but a meere roguery and chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. For this notorious Art,<note place="margin">Ars notoria.</note> is nothing but a vayn ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nay indeed a moſt notorious peece of Roguery, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by Figures, Characters, and vnknowne names: alſo contayning many ſpeeches, concluding in them ſtrange and vnknowne ſignifications, which a man muſt learne and repeate, alwayes obſeruing a continencie in his Diet, and ſometimes to puniſh and macerate himſelfe, would not do amiſſe, if he meane to attaine to the perfect knowledge of this ſcience, which <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> doth vtterly deny:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> 96. <hi>Art.</hi> 1.</note> For, hee ſaith, hee that doth vſe this, can attaine to no ſuch kinde of knowledge, and that the Deuill inuocated by it, cannot infuſe any knowledge, or illuminate the intellect, although hee is able to deliuer the rudiments of ſome kinde of Art: for the Deuill doth onely worke to infatuate and befoole them that exerciſe or ſtudy it. Nor is it auaile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able for any Doctor in this Art, to produce the Examples of <hi>Daniel</hi> and his fellowes, who abſtayning from meate and drinke, came to ſuch a perfect knowledge: for they did not abſtaine from thoſe meates by the vaine obſeruation of this notorious Art, but leaſt they ſhould be defiled with the meate of the Gentiles, which was forbidden them by God: therefore not without deſert they were indued with knowledge aboue the reſt. And <hi>Solomon</hi> begging know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God to gouerne his people, did obtaine it of the Holy Ghoſt. Other vaine obſeruations of this Art, Diuine <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath learnedly confuted.<note place="margin">Aug. lib. <hi>2</hi> de Doctrina Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiana.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Corolarium. <hi>Sine</hi> KOPONIS.</head>
               <p>THus you ſee I haue confuted al the ſuperſtitions of your Art by Art; beating downe the opinions of many
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:12869:47"/>that obſerue times to trauel, marchandiſe, build, and the like, haue diſplaid in the liuelyeſt colours I can your knauery, in ſeducing and blinding the ignorant and beleeuing people, ſet forth your knauery in caſting figures, calculating deaths, and Natiuities, telling of Fortunes, raiſing of Spirits, by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantations, Carminations, Annuall Obſeruations, making Aſtrologicall Images, expreſt the diuelliſhneſſe of your Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uination, Idolatrie, and vaine Obſeruation. Therefore if you can ſpeake any thing in the defence of your Art, or more then I haue ſpoken in the offence of it, beginne, and I will hearken to you with a more diligent attention then I thinke you haue done me. With that he began to rouſe himſelfe vp, and as I thought would haue made his Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall diſcourſe, but that he was interrupted by a loud noiſe of Officers that ſtood beating againſt the dore, mingled with the high voyce of a man, that did nothing but call Rogue, Raſcall, Cheater, Impoſtor, which words I perceiued by the Figure-Caſters countenance did not well pleaſe him, but at laſt (forced by their clamors, much againſt his will) he opened the doore and let them in, who inſtantly attach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, by vertue of a warrant, for couſning a poore Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier of fiueteene pound, holding him in hand, that hee would finde out nine Oxen hee had loſt at ſeuerall times in the Countrey. But to conclude, they firſt hurryed him to the next Iuſtice, who vpon the complaint of the poore man was committed to Newgate, but how he ſpedde, or what mulct or puniſhment he ſuffered, either in purſe or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I leaue it to thoſe that will beſtow the coſt to looke ouer the Records of Newgate.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:12869:47"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
